The science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport, play, and
life. Welcome to perform.
I'm Dr. Andy Galpin. I am a professor
and scientist and the executive director
of the human performance center at
Parker University. Today I'm speaking
with Dr. Lenny Wearsma. Lenny is a
director of sports and performance
psychology for the Olympic sports teams
at the University of California,
Berkeley. And today you're going to
learn a number of tactics and tools to
help you perform at your best mentally.
Lenny does an excellent job of breaking
down what we now understand
scientifically about confidence and how
to better use selft talk. You're also
going to learn a lot about
visualization. What is it? How does it
work? And specifically exactly what to
do to get the most impact out of it.
With all that said, I hope you enjoy
today's conversation with Dr. Lenny
Wearsma. Dr. Lenny Wearsma.
>> Andy, I actually wanted to start in a
place of recency. Few days ago, the
whole world watched Alex Hunnled climb
up a skyscraper and this hurts my entire
soul to say this, but the entire time
watching that, I kept thinking this is
obviously fairly easy for him
physically. There was some challenges,
but that was by far, and again, this is
going to really hurt me saying this,
this was a psychological challenge. Just
at the very basic start here, what does
psychology, what does the brain, how
does this even look when someone is
doing something as crazy as Alex
climbing up a building like that? Where
do we even start to think about this?
I've never worked with Alex. Alex is a
special person for so people who aren't
him like you and I. To try to even have
a sense of what that's like for him is
impossible to do. It's a great example
of we're all seeing the same things, but
we're all seeing very different things
and feeling different things. I've
worked with athletes who do extreme
things, and I have some insight perhaps
and maybe what some of that was like for
him. Um, I mean, the first thing my
nephews were reaching out, hey, what do
you think? Is it going to be like it's a
10-second delay. Is that going to be
needed?
And like, no.
Like one thing I've learned about
extreme sport athletes is that if it's
not a 100% yes, then it's a 100% no.
And like this is important to understand
like the risk involved with it. Because
I think at the heart of doing these
things is the concept of the psychology
of risk for all of us. The consequence
of what he had is the same. a mistake,
um him being overconfident,
an earthquake, wind, like things in his
control, things out of our control. For
everybody, the consequence is the same.
It's sheer death. Yeah.
>> But the risk is very different
>> because he's not going to do that. He's
not going to go into doing that if he
has doubt in his mind about his ability
to do it.
And actually, I think that's pretty
phenomenal to know what it took for him
to buy that kind of confidence, to build
that kind of confidence over time. I
remember when he did Alcap,
he spent, to my understanding, an entire
year doing a stretching routine so that
he can do a move with his leg that
probably lasts about 3 seconds.
I wish I had something in my life that
I'd be willing to dedicate a year for a
3se secondond thing. Mo most humans
actually probably have some capability
of doing great things. But how many of
us are really willing to put that kind
of like all-in investment in. So those
little things, those little details in
his the way he's approached doing
everything is probably explains a lot to
me. What I find fascinating is you see
all these the footage of the people who
are inside those windows of that
building and he's standing outside
there, you know, no safety net, anything
>> and just his ability to to focus and
part of me was thinking like why didn't
they shut that building down?
>> I thought the same thing. I was
>> these people know their cell phones in
his face through this window and they're
waving in there. Do they know how
dangerous that is for them to try to
distract him and yet he has probably a
superhuman level of focus to be able to
know when he needs to engage and
interact and know where he needs to put
his focus. Um so you know when you when
you look at that performance that was a
performance of a lifetime in my mind.
>> Sure. and how eloquently and how
composed he did that. And it there were
times where it actually looked like he
was having fun doing it, like taking it
in, standing at the ledge, looking down,
like that amount of joy that that
brought him probably is the I'm guessing
one of the big motivational forces for
him to do that. But that that ability to
know 100% that he's going to pull that
off and go into it was the deciding
factor, which
makes it even more interesting in my
mind. I think we might want to know, oh,
he might fall. I don't think he ever
thought he was ever going to fall on
that thing. I think it's interesting to
study the extreme sort of sport thing
because even though most of us don't
aspire to do those things, we can all
learn certain aspects about how they
approach it and how they going about it
piece of it. The misnomer about Alex
Hnold is that he doesn't feel fear.
>> Please walk the world through this.
tight. This seems to be
>> So, he goes on fMRI and he's shown
pictures of things that would trigger
most people and he has what's referred
to as depressed amydala function,
meaning he's his brain isn't responding
with the intensity. Therefore, he's not
afraid of what he does.
>> He doesn't feel fear. He biologically
has no ability to or a dampened ability
to sense feel fear. Therefore, these
things are not hard for him cognitively.
>> Totally minimizes and dehumanizes what
he what he does.
>> It's also not academically true. No, I
know. It's Yeah, it's not crazy. That
was interesting. I've been a little bit
out of the extreme sport world in quite
a bit of time and to be able to
experience that from afar was actually
really fun for me to do.
>> I mean, your academic background as a
scientist in this field as well as a
clinician. You mentioned it briefly, but
in case folks glossed over that, you
continue to work with some of the
world's best athletes. Yeah.
>> You've worked with extreme sport
athletes. I think your I think it was
your first sobatical where you looked at
the surfers,
>> big way surfers. Again, I can't think of
a better person to have this
conversation with because well, no one
can play armchair psychologists. Yeah.
>> Right.
>> We certainly can say what of lessons
have you learned again in the research,
what have you published, other
scientists and then again what have you
seen in that extreme. So, kind of
continuing on this theme,
>> I would love to hear your insights on
those folks you have worked with, people
that have jumped off of helicopters on
big mountains and skied the whole thing
down. Are they the same as Alex's
supposedly true or not? Let's just say
it's true. Who cares? Do they not feel
fear? Like, how does it actually happen
when someone can do something as risk
tolerant or intolerant as this?
>> What the hell is actually happening to
these people? Cuz I could never do that.
There's no chance. I don't think I
could. I don't. Can you train that?
>> Maybe this is the question.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Is that a trainable skill or is Alex
born that way? Are these people that
surf Maverick, is that natural to them
or was that something they trained into?
One of the things that struck me about
working with that population is, you
know, the work that I do. I'm supposed
to be an expert in, you know, mental
skill and mental performance. And
>> this feels good for me to hear you say
an expert.
>> Yeah.
>> Virtually none of those individuals who
do that work with someone like me. They
put hours and hours and hours into
building it. I don't believe that
anyone's born to be able to do what they
do. I think they start small. They make
a lot of mistakes. They learn from the
best. The commitment to them being
experts at what they do. I did a study
in which um I interviewed people who do
these very extreme backcountry skiing
and snowboarding, but they stopped
taking the helicopters and they climbed.
So now they have two aspects of it. They
have the ascent which is dangerous in
and of itself
>> and they have the descent which is
dangerous in and of itself
>> as well as now you're really tired.
>> You're doing that descent when you're
exhausted already as you climb the
mountain.
>> They probably know as much about weather
and big wave surfers know as much about
oceanography as the people who have
multiple PhDs who study those things.
Like that's the dedication that they
that they took to get to the level of
studying the craft and and doing what
they do.
Um so not only have they not done any
formal training most of them and the
mental side of it I think it's just they
they have a desire to do it I think one
of the big m misnomers is the risk piece
I think a lot of people assume that the
thrillseeking is a big motivation for
doing it and it's very rarely why
someone does these things is for the
thrill of it as a matter of fact I mean
imagine being in a in a airplane and
having extreme tur turbulence. Who likes
that? Who wants that? Who thinks, "Oh,
this is why I want to fly, so I can
experience thoughts that I might die." I
don't think any of them have that or
they probably wouldn't be doing it in
the first place. And when I when I first
started to kind of figure out the
motivation behind some of these
individuals, I think that was an
assumption. I didn't bring that in, but
I think a lot of people, oh, they do it
for the thrillseeking. They do it for
the risk-taking piece. And surprisingly,
it's not that simple. And that's
actually not why most of them do it. I
think if you or I have a talent and we
have a skill and it's something that we
absolutely love to do and we have a
passion for it, that's a driving force,
not the notion that we may fail doing it
and we may suffer these big consequences
as a result of it. So that piece of it
and and being really aware of the
confidence piece is a dangerous thing.
The confidence piece for a basketball
player shooting free throws is a
dangerous thing. Imagine the confidence
piece of someone who who overthinks
their ability in a moment and takes
risks. As a matter of fact, the approach
that we might take in a traditional
sport setting with like being in the
zone, right? Oh, yeah. I can't miss. So,
then keep going. Don't stop.
>> Yeah. Temperature jacks, we call that,
right?
>> If you ever think that you're in that
state, in one of those sports, you need
to stop and get yourself out of that
state because that's when you're going
to make a mistake. That's when you're
going to you're going to make that that
one more that you shouldn't have done
that might cost you. And so they're
really good at regulating that notion of
okay I'm feeling too confident here.
Most athletes don't ever say I'm feeling
too confident right now. I think most
athletes are like they want to get in
that state but extreme sport athletes
actually that's a very dangerous place
for them to be. So the confidence piece
is very different in that world than I
have seen in most traditional sports
that that I I work with. Is there a way
to identify? Are there tells when you're
in that spot?
>> When you're getting away with things
that you shouldn't have gotten away
with, so you're cutting corners before
you're really ready to do it and you
knew, "Oh, I got away with that one."
You're not going to get away with the
next one doing it. I think that's a big
teller is they're honest with themselves
about that one. Like, okay, I got lucky
on that one. It's time for me to pull
out. But it what it looks like often in
in big way surfing is they paddle back
to the channel where there is no waves
coming. So they can get themselves out
of that and they can kind of like, okay,
where am I with things? Let me regulate.
Let me get back to like feeling the
energy of the ocean and stuff so I'm not
just going to jump on the next wave that
I can find and see if I can top the last
one I just did.
>> It felt like the the crash was a big the
wipeout was a really big theme.
>> Yeah.
>> Why did that matter so much? What were
those elite servers doing to mitigate
that issue of the wipeout?
>> They actually focused on what it would
be like if it were to happen and they
prepared for what they were going to do.
They had a plan. Virtually everything
that we'd have some fear over and we
worry about something happening. If we
can just say, "Okay, if that happens,
what's my plan going to be?" And we
believe in the plan, that's like a
massive psychological safety net. And
then that's what alleviates the fear.
the fear the fear will remain
but and so the amount of time they spend
visualizing they spend holding their
breath they spend becoming a lot more um
flexible and knowing how to position
themselves and like visualizing that and
getting into like smaller instances of
that and that okay if this happens to me
this is how I'm going to handle it this
is this is how I'm going to I'm going to
survive it once they have that down then
I think that it becomes less about the
wipe out and more about the the
performance on the wave itself perhaps,
but that that part absolutely has to
happen first. The presenting sponsor of
this podcast is Momentous. Momentus
makes the highest quality supplements on
the market, period. I literally spent
years vetting their products, company,
and leadership team before officially
partnering with them in 2023. Every
single one of Momentous's products is
thirdparty tested to ensure quality, and
many are even NSF certified for sport.
Now, while I love all their products,
I'm incredibly excited about their new
Fiber Plus prebiotic. Almost everyone is
seeking more energy, improved recovery,
and better performance. But most people
are missing a key foundation to their
overall health, and that's getting
enough good fiber. In fact, 95% of
Americans are failing to hit the
recommended daily amount of fiber. Fiber
powers gut health, which we know drives
long-term performance. Proper gut health
allows for better nutrient absorption,
energy stability, recovery, inflammation
control, and much more. I personally
simply mix a scoop of their cinnamon
flavor and some water every night. And
by doing so, I make sure I'm covering
any gaps I might have in my daily fiber
intake that I try to get through eating
a balanced whole food diet. If you'd
like to try Fiber Plus or any of
Momenus' best-in-class supplements, just
go to livemus.com/galpin
and use the code galpin for up to 35%
off your first order. Again, that's live
momentous.com/galpin
and use the code galpin for up to 35%
off your first order. People will
describe this idea differently, but this
is you run fear to the end.
>> Yeah.
>> What if what if it actually happened,
right? And then actually live in that
moment. I'd love for you to share more
about the visualization piece because I
caught that just now as you said it and
I have always personally just thought of
visualization as almost
using your brain to practice the good
stuff. I'm just realizing as you said
that I don't actually know if I spent
that much time thinking about the
visualization from the negative side. So
the two-part question is what really is
that visualization of the second part?
The second question here to that is in
general what are people doing maybe
wrong with visualization? How can they
do it better?
>> For the duration of the time I've been
in this field, 30 years of all the
mental skills that have been researched
to be effective, visualization seems to
be the one that keeps coming out on top.
And so I've, you know, suggested it,
I've worked with athletes on it. But it
really actually hasn't been until more
recently that I've really really truly
understood how powerful it can be. So
it starts with the why to your point of
like visualizing the things you do well.
There's very distinct uses of
visualization. So you can visualize for
confidence and in that that's the case
you want to see yourself in moments
where you're doing well. And when
athletes are going for the first time in
the Olympic Games or a World
Championship or an NC2A championship, I
always say to them like, imagine when
you were a kid in your backyard and you
were pretending like you were taking the
two free throws to win the game or
you're at the baseball field pretending
like you were the person at bat when
it's bottom of the ninth inning, bases
loaded, two outs. Like you've always
wanted to be in that moment. And so like
visualizing yourself so that you can
build that confidence I think is
traditionally one of the things that
most people have used visualization for.
Visualization can be for coping.
Actually some of the best uses of
visualization is coping. Visualization
meaning you imagine what might go wrong
and you imagine what you will do in that
moment. When I work with teams, I
usually I'll say never reference the
Navy Seals
because no one's going to be a Navy
Seal. And I I I don't like reading books
where they reference the Navy Seals.
>> It's like a chef cooking with bacon.
Like a true chef is like, "No, I'm not
going to use it. I'm not going to use
it. It's a game."
>> Nor and I work with swimmers. I've been
working in swimming a long time. Will I
use Michael Phelps as an example because
another for another reason like no one's
going to be Michael Phelps.
However, you have to use Michael Phelps
when it comes to visualization because
that moment in the Beijing Olympics
where his goggles filled up with water
and he had eight gold medals riding on
the line.
>> Before you keep going, can you actually
like actually tell that story because it
is it's remarkable. Just a little bit of
context on that story. I don't want
>> 2008 Michael Phelps's slated to swim
eight events. The previous gold medal
record was seven set by Mark Spitz in
1972. And the big question of could
Michael Phelps break that record. His
final event was the 200 butterfly and he
dove in the water and his goggles had um
come off of his face and they filled
with water when they kind of reset
themselves. And so he swam um seven out
of eight laps blind.
And there's some lore about like what
allowed him to prepare for that moment.
Um there are stories of his coach Bob
Balman early in his career where he
would remove his goggles and not allow
him to swim with his goggles at a big
race so that he could you know be in
that moment where okay what if this
happens and he would visualize over and
over again and count his strokes and so
he knew exactly what he needed to do. He
didn't have to see it. He had done it so
many times. He talks about like his cap
ripping and he can't wear someone else's
cap because it has has he can't use some
so he's got to turn it inside out and
that wherewithal of being able to like
think through that in the most stressful
he visualizes those things happening. So
coping visualization is a really
powerful one where we see ourselves in
situations where we imagine what might
happen and then you learn and practice
coping techniques and tools so that when
you're in that situation you've seen
yourself and you've seen yourself doing
it the right way. So that's that's a
huge part of visualization is the coping
piece.
Familiarization. So if you haven't yet
done something and you're going to be in
that in that moment, you want to see
yourself in advance for that. So if I
will work with the swimmer, I'll tell
them get to the pool, locate the ready
room, which is where they sit all eight
athletes at the final before they get
marched out and practice walking and how
long is the walk going to be and where
are the lights going to be. And I'll
imagine that if I were to be, you know,
nervous or afraid of being in a podcast,
I would have come to this room without
you knowing. and I would have looked in
here and I would have seen the setup and
then I would have went outside for a
little bit and I would have imagined
myself there without me being there. So,
it starts with the why
um with the visualization piece first
and then what you visualize
has to be based on what it is that you
want to get out of it. Is it to learn
something that you haven't done before?
Is it to modify something? I work with
tennis players. They've literally taken
millions of swings before they've come
to college and then they have to make a
technical adjustment and that has to not
reverse but like they're starting over
basically as noviceses. Imagine having
something that you do such a habit of
and then having to make a technical
adjustment. So the visualization with
that would be the increase the mental
reps of them doing it the right way. And
so that would be a different form of
visualization.
um massive tool. Uh generally speaking,
I I I don't want people doing
visualization before they go to bed. I
can't count the number of athletes where
they'll be in their hotel room the night
before a competition. They want to
visualize that before they go to sleep
and now they're not sleeping for the
next two hours because if they did it
right,
>> they're not going to be able to sleep.
Their brain's engaged. You always want
to have emotion as part of the
visualization. like that emotional piece
is maybe more important than the visual
piece of it. And so like you don't want
to do it there. Visualization does not
have to take a long time.
The most powerful things to visualize
are short repeatable things that you can
see over and over again. You can see it
in different ways. And I think that's a
big part of it. So, you know, most
people if they're going to visualize
something, they want to sit down for a
moment first and say, "Okay, not just
close your eyes and take a couple deep
breaths and visualize." You need to
know, okay, what do I want to get out of
it? Those things I listed before. What
do I want the visualization to do? And
then based on that, what are a couple
things that I want to visualize for this
one session alone? Um, so those are
those are some of the the big things is
feeling what it's going to feel like.
Athletes move and so they have to feel.
I've been doing a lot more with using
equipment or clothing while they
visualize. It's going to sound really
bizarre, but
>> the whole field is so go ahead.
>> A goalkeeper is going to have their
goalkeeper gloves when they visualize or
a surfer is going to be lying on their
surfboard when they visualize because
you're smelling wax. Sense of smell is
such a powerful scent. And now you smell
your wax when you're doing it. And that
brings emotions that you get a sense of
anxiousness and nervousness and
excitement with that. Should you put
your wets suit on first and then lie on
your surfboard to do it? Yes. There's
some evidence that the closer you can
get. And there's also a little bit of
evidence, although it's a little bit
sketchy where we associate certain
emotions with the clothing or uniforms
that we wear. And so like that's another
added component where if you can at all
I've mentioned swimming a couple times
have your tech suit on, have your
goggles on, have your cap on when you're
doing it, you're feeling what you might
feel in the moment. I have several
follow-ups to that. Um just real quick,
when you say does it have to be long?
Are these 25 minute sessions? Give me a
rough idea of generally how long you're
thinking about a visualization session
should be terms of minutes. I work with
athletes whose time is of the essence
and if they can give me full focus 10
minutes of visualization I think that's
a huge win
>> 10 minutes daily
>> 10 minutes
>> twice a day once a day
>> depends on how much time they have I
think more is better
>> but I think we all should also should
put in context a little bit the athletes
I work with today mostly
>> I'm at um Cal Berkeley I work um in our
athletics department I work with eight
of our teams at Cal that's my primary
full-time job. I'm still working with
professional athletes on the side, but
like my day-to-day work is with these
student athletes.
>> Given the fact that you're at Berkeley,
not football, that probably means you're
dealing with a level of athletes that
are not only division one,
>> but they're usually very highly ranked
nationally, right? Your swim teams, your
water polos, like this is a very good
sport at Berkeley.
>> I work mostly with our Olympic sports,
>> which are very good in at Berkeley
generally most of the time. I think in
Paris 2024 games we had 54 current or
former Cow Bears and if you look at
their medal totals they would have been
in the top 10 of countries.
>> That's a better way to frame it.
>> This is a high level and yet they are
also attending classes at Cal Berkeley
one of the premier academic institutions
in the world. And so for me to ask them
to take 10 minutes a day is a big ask.
and I will not ask him to do it if I
don't believe that it was going to be a
good investment for him.
>> So, is that a a general rule you want
most your people doing around if you
can? 10 minutes of visualization. Is
that a pretty standard protocol for you
guys?
>> Yeah, as you get into close to
competitive like NC2As for our divers
or, you know, NC2A for tennis or
something, then probably want to ramp it
up a little bit as you go into that into
the maybe a couple weeks out of it. But
I mean, if you really do it right and do
it well, if you can give yourself 10
minutes of visualization, I think it it
could change your entire performance.
>> Could you give me an example or a little
bit of an understanding of how a
non-athlete
could or would want to use visualization
like this? If I can say, okay, 10
minutes a day, I'll give you that, but
why would I even care about it? Or is
this only for those trying to win?
anything that we have to do to perform.
You know, the field of sports psychology
is more
being referred to as performance
psychology today because we've morphed
into realms that were outside of the
traditional sport setting. So,
performing arts and medicine and
military and so if you're taking an exam
and you typically get really nervous
before your exams, visualize yourself
sitting at your desk before you receive
the exam. What are you doing to cope
with that? What do you do when the if
you're still doing it in person? What
are you doing when the professor comes
over and hands out the exams? What kind
of breathing are you doing the first
time you read over the first couple
questions? What are you saying to
yourself? How are you regulating
yourself? If you're if you have to do a
a presentation to a group at work and
there's funding on the line for it, then
you want to visualize what that
performance might look like for you. One
of the most nervous at the most nervous
time I've ever been in my life. I had to
uh officiate a wedding over 200 people
in sign language.
>> And the bride was deaf. This is going
back 30 years. And there was a young
girl on the team who was deaf. And she
went from knowing me without knowing
sign language one year to me coming home
fluent in sign language. And then she
reached out some 15 years after she had
done and she asked if I would officiate
her wedding in sign language. And that
was a massive like honor to do that. But
I did not want to mess that up. So now
I'm nervous. I'm in Long uh Long Island.
It's like 100 degrees outside. I'm
wearing my suit. The amount of time I
spent visualizing doing that performance
in sign language was massive for me
because it's like I'd already done it a
hundred times before I stood up to do
it. So, so pick a scenario in your life
where you have something coming up that
there's something on the line for it and
ask yourself, what might happen? What do
I not want to happen? And see yourself
cope through that if it happens. What's
your plan? Seeing exactly what you want
to happen happen. How are you going to
feel when you do that? It's actually
super super powerful
and a great way of practicing this. So
when you and I were chatting before
this, we were talking a little bit about
sleep. And one of the sleep tools right
now that's a big sleep tool is sleep
stories. And so we ruminate. We're lying
in bed. We're thinking about tomorrow's
competition. We're thinking about
tomorrow's exam. We're thinking about
tomorrow's job interview. And so our
minds are racing. And so sleep stories
are designed so that you can unhook from
those thoughts and you can give your
your mind to something else. And the
reason why they're so powerful is they
create a lot of detail. So now you're
trying to visualize what that story is.
And now that leads to cognitive fatigue,
which is going to make you fall asleep.
And you're no longer thinking about
those things. And so while I do not
think I would visualize a performance
before I go to sleep, I would definitely
tap into sleep stories as a way of like
practicing
vivid visualization because if you can
imagine that train ride, that's by the
way, I think those are the most popular
sleep stories or train stories. If you
can practice imagining that with detail,
then you can practice imagining that
performance in front of your board of
directors or in front of your eighth
grade class or something. It's really
funny you said that because many years
ago I started writing down sleep tips
for the athletes that I was working
with. And one of the ones that I would
use all the time is if you wake up and
you have a racing mind. I would always
say the example I do is I go all the way
back to 1995 and I try to remember the
entire starting lineup for the Seattle
Mariners. Right. Because I'm like that's
a huge childhood memory. And one of the
mistakes people make here is they try to
turn their brain off.
>> Yeah.
>> When this is happening, right? and it
does not work. I actually engage as hard
as I possibly can in a nonstressful
when failure doesn't matter.
>> Yeah.
>> Because you actually induce that
cognitive fatigue and you're completely
removing yourself from the thing that
was probably keeping you awake. And I
just started figuring out I go back to
sleep immediately like when this happens
and you fast forward probably 10 years
and at Absolute Rest now we use these
sleep stories and similar tools
constantly. And I'm like, I nailed it.
Like, I was so ahead of the research.
Like, I figured this thing out. And
there's a It's really interesting how
people do not associate the difference
between turning your brain off.
>> Yeah.
>> And just turning it in a different
direction, right? And so, you don't want
to if you lay there the entire time
trying to think, turn off brain, like,
well, just just expect to lay there for
a long time telling your brain to turn.
It's just not going to work.
>> The term that's used for that is
unhooking.
>> Interesting. I know some of you are
listening to this right now, but imagine
a hook in something and and it's it's
not going to let go of it. That's what
rumination is. That's when we get into
something in our mind that we can't let
go of
>> until we give us something else to be
thinking about. That's what that did for
you is to is to go and just think about
something entirely different or what the
sleep stories are designed to do.
>> Um so any rate, I know we're going to go
on a lot of these long tangents back to
the visualization piece. I just think
it's such a a a powerful tool and trying
to play with like techniques like using
equipment or clothing or um you know
uniforms or something to make it a
little bit more real.
>> I have some some questions about that
tactic. But before we get there, I want
to know if I'm doing some visualization,
do you have a rough sense of how often I
should visualize what I'm just going to
call the performance itself? So my
technique, my strategy, the stuff I'm
going to do, right? I'm gonna hit this
part of my pitch and then I'm gonna hit
that part of the pitch and then I'm
gonna get to that part of the story,
whatever. The things I'm trying to do
and just remembering my own, you know,
technique versus I forget how you called
it, but the the fear part of it is like,
well, what if what if goes wrong? How
much time should I spend on the front
side versus the backside or the
performance side versus the failure?
Going into a session where you're going
to be visualizing something very
difficult, I would always start with
what's easy and what you already have
confidence in first. Like if I if I meet
with a team, how many of you visualize
you doing something really well? About
half the team kind of raises their hand.
And what are the rest of you thinking
about? Are the things I keep messing up?
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah.
>> Definitely don't want to see yourself
failing.
>> Yeah.
>> Some of this is not even visualizing the
performance itself. And some of it's
visualizing the leadup to the
performance and what's your your routine
and what are you eating the morning of
and what are you what are you doing when
you get dressed and so some of it's not
even the performance itself. is just the
the leadup to it. Some of it is just a
very small aspect of the performance
that you just really want to nail. Like
like it's all going to come down to this
right here. And I really need to see
myself doing that the right way and
feeling it the right way over and over
and over again.
>> And then if you have the time, you could
sort of link all those things maybe
start to finish a little bit together.
Today's episode is sponsored by EightLe.
Asleep makes smart mattress covers with
cooling, heating, sleep tracking, and
more. I've personally been sleeping on
an EightLe mattress for more than three
years now, and it's absolutely glorious.
I love it so much that I hate traveling
away from home because I can't sleep on
my EightLe Pod 5. As you'll hear me talk
about endlessly on this podcast, there's
really nothing you can do that makes
more of an impact on your health and
performance than getting a great night
of sleep. And getting great sleep
requires having your body temperature
drop a couple of degrees at night. And
that's hard to do on your own. The Eight
asleep has been a gamecher for me
because I run hot at night or as my wife
calls it, I'm a furnace. If I don't have
something like an eight helping me cool
down, I'll wake up in the middle of the
night overheating and not feeling great.
This is something I've also found in
many people that I coach, especially
those who are really physically active.
The Pod 5 is the latest generation of
the EightLe mattress covers and it can
go on any mattress, heats or cools each
side of the bed from 55 to 110 degrees
Fahrenheit and provides highfidelity
sleep tracking. If you'd like to try
eight, go to 8LE.com/perform
and use the code perform to save up to
$350 off your Pod 5 Ultra. You get 30
days to try it at home and return it if
you don't love it, but I'm confident
that you will. I certainly love mine and
would never consider returning it.
Asleep currently ships to the US,
Canada, the UK, and select countries in
the EU, and even Australia. Again,
that's eight asleep.com/perform
and use the code perform to save up to
$350.
When you talked earlier about thinking
about what can go wrong, how do you
balance that with putting yourself in
too much negative selft talk? Right? So,
if I'm always sitting there thinking
about all the things that go wrong, am I
actually just harming my own confidence?
Am I walking in then anticipating
failure? How do I know if I'm there? And
what does that process look like?
>> A really powerful way of doing it is to
go back to something that you just
failed at and then kind of recreate it
again as soon as you can after, not
immediately after because you're too
emotional, but you know, somebody who
who dropped a really really close match
that they should have won, for example,
or really had a bad performance. So go
back and then try as much as possible to
think about what you were thinking about
when that was happening. What were you
trying to do to cope? What was your
selft talk? What type of thoughts did
you have? And now we can get a sense of
do those help you or do they hurt you?
It's not about it being negative selft
talk. It's about whether it's helping
you or hurting you. So you start with
that first like go back what was that
thought process? What was that like for
you? Okay now let's do it differently.
And now so what you're doing is you are
not hiding behind the fact that this
occurred or that it might happen again
but you're capitalizing on the fact that
you've done it one time and now what was
it what would you do differently this
time around? There's nothing wrong
actually with seeing yourself failing
something as long as you're turning that
into a better result next time it
happens. Okay? So if you've been through
it one time, recreate it as closely as
possible. be super aware of what you
were doing, what you were saying, what
you were thinking, how you were
breathing. Try to recreate that. Okay,
now let's make adjustments to that. And
it almost writes itself.
>> They usually don't need me for that
piece of it, although it might help.
>> I do I do ask athletes a lot like when
you perform your best typically. Let's
let's write down a couple performances
that you've done fairly recently that
you've done really well. Now, let's go
back let's go back to the morning of
Let's go back to right before.
what were your behaviors? What were the
things that you were thinking? And it's
a great learning tool for them to be
able to do that. And often they're
thinking and doing things very
differently than they were in moments in
which they had a really poor performance
sitting right there in front of them. So
we want to tap into that. And every
single person performer is different.
And so it's like that's one of the first
things I do if I work with an athlete or
a team is I just always come from the
fact that I've done this for a long
time. And the most successful people
I've worked with all do it differently.
And if this this super elite athlete
says one negative thing to herself, then
she's going to spiral the rest of the
time. And this athlete over here, if
they try to be positive with themselves
and be a little bit of forgiving for
themselves, spirals them in the opposite
direction. So like we have to really
really study what makes us our best and
it's different for absolutely everybody.
The negative thinking part can be a
dangerous thing for a lot of people who
have been taught that you shouldn't
think negatively
and I think most people need to be a
little bit more forgiving in in
performance spaces because the amount of
pressure people put on themselves and
the perfectionism that comes with elite
performance is very very strong. So yes,
if I'm going to air on the side of one
or the other, it's like, okay, be a
little more forgiving of yourself.
However, there are times where negative
selft talk is actually going to be the
thing that's going to get you out of
this state of darkness. We can get a lot
into the selft talk piece. I think it's
one of the another most powerful tool.
And I think it's more powerful than
visualization in the context of in the
moment that we're doing it because
that's what you're thinking of in that
moment.
>> Yeah. I mean, I guess it's fair to say
visualization is probably something
you're going to do pre and post.
>> Yeah. that you're not going to stop and
think through. I mean,
>> golfers can before their shot.
>> Of course,
>> free throw, you know, basketball players
can do it before they take if it's a
selfinitiated task. Yes. But
>> well, you'll see this in golf every
single shot.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh you in fact, if you pay attention to
caddies,
really common thing for a caddy to say
is, "Okay, see it? Okay, feel it. You
got the feeling." Like they won't even
ask. Very rarely do they say things
like, "Oh, you're at 97 m. We got to,
you know, pitch it over." It's usually
like, "What's a shot?" "Yeah, we're
gonna You feel it? Do you see it?" "No."
Like, "It's not feeling right." And I
have them walk back the ball, readress
it. Okay, now I see the shot. And then
they walk away.
>> Caddies are really good about stopping
talking. Once they feel like they have
the feeling of it, then they just shut
up and walk away.
>> Yeah.
>> This is one thing that I I've seen you
uh talk about a lot as well is this
coaching
idea. So you've given us I think some
great tools on visualization but I would
love to hear more on this selft talk
right now and then I would love to get
into this difference between literally
selft talk versus coaching right so I'm
either coaching or leading somebody else
how do I communicate with them to put
them in the right spot but let's start
with the self what other things should
we be paying attention to with that
selft talk how do I know if I'm doing
too much negative selft talk or too much
positive what does that all mean and how
do we do
First thing I'm going to say is we
should not be distinguishing categories
of positive versus negative.
>> Amazing.
>> It should be screwed up right out the
gates.
>> It should be whether it's effective or
not effective. That's the big thing.
>> Ah because it can be negative but
effective.
>> Exactly.
>> And positive but ineffective.
>> Perfect.
>> So it's not about negative or positive.
We'll take that off the table. It's is
this effective for you or not effective
for you. If you and I were to start, I
would ask you to write down the names of
two or three people in your life who you
really admire, you really trust. You
know they've got your back. They can
look you in the eye and say anything to
you and you know it's coming from a
place of they want me to do well.
Two out of those three are people you
should know personally.
One could be someone you so look up to
in a field because of what they've
accomplished that you just have that
much admiration and respect for what
they've done. So I would start with okay
let's identify two or three people who
would be those individuals for you. I
think it's really important first to
start with those two or three people
and then I'm going to ask you to think
about a scenario that you might find
yourself in that one of your best
friends might be in. So something that
you might find yourself in but have
someone else in that scenario and
they're struggling or they're stressed
about it or they're feeling anxious
about or they're worried about it.
What would you say to them?
So one of the most powerful aspects of
selft talk is psychological distancing.
Psychological distancing is when we're
in that moment emotionally and we want
to create some distance from that and
the place from which we're talking
or listening to ourselves in our mind we
can create some distance and that
usually comes to being a lot more
effective psychological distancing. So
you've got first person selft talk which
is I second person selft talk which is
you or your name and then you've got
third person selft talk which is a whole
other person and one thing that we found
to be super effective is to come out of
a place of the first person selft talk
at least to a place of talking to
yourself
when you said the difference between
selft talk and coaching that's what came
to my mind is you Actually, they're the
same thing.
>> Interesting.
>> You should be coaching yourself.
>> It's the same. That's what your selft
talk ought to be. Most of us actually
are probably really, really good at your
best friends dealing with something. We
know exactly what to say. Why? Because
we're not in the emotion of it. And if
we can practice self-t talk tools that
distance oursel from the I and what I'm
feeling to the you, it can be a very,
very, very powerful thing.
If you go back to
the names that you wrote down on the
piece of paper and I want listeners to
maybe pause for a moment and if you were
to write down the list of two or three
people who are really really powerful in
your life and then if you're in a
situation that's bringing you stress or
something.
Imagine what one of those individuals
would say to you and imagine it in their
voice and them using your name to say
it. It could be massively massively
powerful. That's the greatest
psychological distance that we can get.
Number one, it comes from not a place of
emotion, but number two, it comes from
an authority who we trust and who we
believe in. That person can be with you
up on that building. If it's Alex Honold
or that surfboard, if it's a big wave
surfer or that baseball pitcher who
just, you know, walked the last three
batters and thinks he's about to get
pulled. Like, imagine going to that
person in your mind. The selft talk
piece is so so powerful. There's some
evidence that what we're thinking is a
bigger predictor of our confidence than
anything else. What we're thinking in
the moment is a bigger predictor of
confidence than any other thing that
could have brought us confidence.
There's some evidence that what we're
thinking in the moment is a bigger
predictor of our happiness than any
other factor. Money in the bank, who
we're with, it's powerful those those
type of thoughts. So do a lot of work
first reflecting on when we're in our
performance environments, what are the
type of things that we say to ourel and
not as a positive or negative, but does
that help me? Does that hurt me and why?
A lot of reflection of that and then
learning some of these tools where we
can start to separate ourselves from our
own voice and bring in either coaching
ourselves or talking to ourselves. If
you have a nickname for yourself, use
that nickname.
I've been my nickname has been lend dog
since I was a kid. Everywhere I've ever
moved to, people have called me Lund dog
without knowing that the other groups of
people in my life have said that. So if
I'm stressed, I'm going to refer to
myself as Lone Dog in my mind because it
it actually really focuses me and it
really gets me super like, oh yeah,
that's right. I'm Lone Dog. That was an
incredible incredible tip. I can tell
you right now, I'm going to start using
that. I am someone and it doesn't matter
that it's about me, but I am someone who
really enjoys
I'll just call negative feedback at this
point. I actually it doesn't really get
me emotionally in the wrong spot.
>> It's a very positive thing. I I really
enjoy breaking down my
>> effective feedback.
>> Super effective.
>> But I've never thought about using that
second person approach, which again,
I'll tell you right now that I'm going
to do that. That that's incredible. I'm
going to start using that coaching wise
as well. Is it because it allows you to
detach a little bit from the situation
and it's no longer about you and you and
self-worth or anything like that? It is
simply an objective assessment of what
needs to happen. So it it isn't as hard
to take. Is that is that a fair kind of
Andy way to say that?
>> Yeah. The the first person is very
reactive.
>> See, see I said Andy right there by the
way.
>> Oh yeah, that already working.
>> Yeah.
>> Would you have a nickname? That would
have been even better.
>> No, Andy would be good. Ask my daughter,
you'll get a different answer. And
>> so part of it is because if we are just
letting thoughts come passively, which
is what happens, a lot of our thoughts
are very passive, reactive, emotional
thoughts. Most of those fall under the
category of ineffective, whether they're
positive or negative, they they probably
do. So bringing that distance
perspective, that selft talk perspective
reduces some of the emotion associated
with also if I'm the the person dealing
with something and you have an
opportunity to say something to me,
you're not going to beat me up over it.
>> You're not going to say anything that
you think the intention is to make me
any worse or feel worse about what. So
we're actually really good about doing
that. The exercise of writing down the
names first. Number one. Number two, I
did this in a class recently at
Berkeley. I had a chance to be in the
classroom for the first time in a long
time.
>> Yeah, you're retired for the record.
>> I'm retired and it was in a class not it
was in an entrepreneur class and I would
ask these students at Cal like think of
scenarios that you find yourself in over
the course of a semester that are very
challenging for you. Now, write down the
name of a of a really good friend who
you also know are in those scenarios.
So, a teammate or whatever. And then
when they're in it and they shoot you a
text and they express the negative
emotion they're feeling, what's your
response to them? You know exactly what
you need to say. So use that with
yourself a lot more often. Very, very
powerful tool. If you're looking for a
good reference on it, Ethan Cross, he's
at University of Michigan. He's wrote a
book called Chatter. And it's one of the
books that I loan out to athletes a lot.
I usually don't loan out books. For some
context, at Fullerton, before I retired
from Fullerton, I had a floor to ceiling
bookshelf full of books. And when I
moved, I donated a lot to the lab and I
gave a lot away, but I only brought the
books I really wanted to keep. And then
in my office, I have very little space.
I have two small rows of books. So,
anything in that bookshelf,
>> precious real estate.
>> Yeah, Chatter is one of them.
>> Amazing. And I have two copies of the
same book, The Inner Game of Tennis,
written by Timothy Goway in 1977. It was
the first book I ever read that was
anything having to do with sports psych.
It's remarkable. I have the original and
I have the updated version of it. So
anyway, we're getting off a little
tangent, but Chatter is one of those
books that give really good insight and
and sort of like exercises on how to
hone that craft of selft talk.
>> Great. That's amazing. Thank you for
that resource. Um, is there any
evidence, scientific evidence, or have
you just seen it from your practical
experience on when people use that
second person approach, do they tend to
be gentler on themsel? Uh, do they tend
to be more fair? I I'm only saying this
because in this sense, when you talk to
yourself, sometimes there is ineffective
and negative selft talk, right? When you
switch,
>> is that enlightened a little bit? Is
that tend to be more
effective in the sense because we're not
making it about ourselves per se as in
like you're a bad or person. It's more
about the task at hand or is that not
been shown?
>> It will be a lot more forgiving. It will
be a lot more from the place of you're
fine. You're you're making this worse
than it really is. It can actually be
more forceful in some ways, but like
>> Andy, that's not the Andy I used to
know. You're so much tougher than that,
Andy. Come on, dude. you I I know you I
know you you're going to get through
this. You're going to be fine. So sit up
a little straighter and you know that it
could be actually a little bit more
forceful. Very powerful and it it again
comes from a place of positive intent.
There's actually been a lot of research
on these different selft talk
perspectives and that that distance
selft talk perspective virtually always
comes out as a more effective way of
communicating with ourselves. Is that
second person talk something one would
do before the event or best in the event
after or all three?
>> It's in the moment.
>> Yeah,
>> it's it's usually most powerful when
you're in the moment of what it is that
you're doing. Instead of measuring heart
rate, I would have loved to somehow
measure what Alex Hon was saying to
himself on that thing. If we're going to
refer back to that, like that internal
dialogue that he had, I don't know if
anybody could guess what it would have
been like, but it's the most fascinating
thing. If I could get a transcript of
his thoughts
>> and then could we learn how to use that
same tool with ourselves? That to me is
just would be amazing.
>> Well, maybe Lenny, he's just gotten
really comfortable being uncomfortable.
>> Is this the time for a break? I think we
should break now because I'm going to go
break something.
>> I warned you I was going to go here and
I I had to go here. So, you and I are so
much more on the same page than you ever
thought you ever would be. Don't you
dare accuse me of that.
>> The phrase being comfortable being
uncomfortable is oh my goodness, I don't
even know where to start with that. And
I have to be careful because actually a
lot of trusted colleagues of mine use it
regularly. And while I might joke with
them about like it's impossible.
>> Semantically, it's impossible.
>> It's impossible. No, be warm when you're
cold. No, I'm cold. No, be warm. I'm
cold. Be comfortable. And I get the
larger sense of it is like try to be
less uncomfortable. That's the thing.
Try to be less uncomfortable. That's
really what the phrase should be. But
>> if you're listening at home, this is
what academics do.
>> This is what we do with our time. That's
right. Most of research is this. But
>> that's right.
>> You actually should embrace being more
uncomfortable and not want to be
comfortable. That's the secret to
success. That that's just what it comes
down to. Like forget about being
comfortable. That's not going to happen.
You don't want it to happen. Let's not
make that a thing. my friend Ken Wright
out has a book coming out and I think
the title of it is uh everything you
want is on the other side of hard. I
actually I just got a copy. I haven't
read it yet, but it sounds like a
similar kind of approach where very much
Ken's I'll say life philosophy for Ken
is just like get rid of this idea of of
being comfortable.
It works for Ken, but I got a feeling
most people are like what? I'm not doing
that. Right.
What's realistic for people to take out
of an idea?
Like get rid of the idea of being
comfortable. Like what's realistic of
this?
>> I work with endurance athletes a lot and
they often bring up how something hurts
and obviously I mean that's the nature
of what they do and they want to be
comfortable or some and it's like okay
number one you can't do that. I think of
a 200 breaststroker who's swimming in
that last push off the wall. Your lungs
are on fire. But that's what you have to
feel if you're going to set the world
record. Like you're going to set the
world record comfortably. You're going
to qualify for NCAA NC2A comfortably.
Take that off the the table there. If we
have an expectation that we should be
something and we're not. That's what
brings us stress. I want to be
comfortable and I'm not. Therefore, I'm
stressed. Well, it's not because you're
uncomfortable. It's because you have
this expectation that's not very
realistic. And we have to let go some of
those things before. Actually, I'd be
interested in reading that book.
Everything wasn't everything we do is on
the other side of heart. Is that
>> Yeah.
>> I mean, since you and I both did this
last time, we both made pretty big
decisions in our life.
>> In my life, stability has always been
one of the most important things for me.
I love stability. I'm very predictable.
>> I'm very habitual.
>> I know exactly what I'm going to have
for breakfast tomorrow morning. I know
when I'm going to have it. I know where
I'm going. That's how I operate in my
life. When I made the decision to leave
a tenure position at Fullerton to go
into the unknown, it was the scariest
thing I've ever freaking done. And yet,
it got me to a place that I've probably
never been happier in my life. It's just
a little bit of a kind of
I just reflect on that a lot like had I
had I not had gone through that period
of time, the the absolute discomfort of
letting go of a tenure position to go
into something unknown. Um, and I found
myself, this is a total aside, but I
found myself going from a tenure
academic position to working in esports.
>> Yeah, I forgot that.
>> 16-year-old multi-millionaires who don't
care about performance psychology, they
don't care about warming up before. They
just want to grind. So, I went from a
very traditional structured environment
>> to esports. And then six months after I
was in this field, leaving a job of 20
plus years with a tenure position,
the whole industry tanks. And I found
myself looking for a job in six months
after I had a job forever. I would have
had that job forever. And not one time
did I ever regret that decision. And yet
another time where I was like, I got to
figure out my life now. What the hell is
that going to look like for me?
But you got to bet on yourself. That's
such a cliche thing, but I remember very
specifically being in our with our
Rocket League team during scrims for
World Championship. And I knew after
that competition was over, I was likely
going to be looking for another job. And
I had no idea I was going to do. And the
phrase I kept saying to myself, just
freaking bet on yourself.
We mentioned earlier and and I don't
know if you want to get into this, the
confidence piece. Yeah. And confidence
versus belief.
Um,
confidence has been considered to be
maybe the most important factor of
success in performance settings and
certainly in sport settings is the
confidence piece. The longer I've been
in this field, it's the most complex
piece as well. The confidence piece is
fleeting. It changes sometimes moment to
moment. If we rely on being confident to
do well, we're screwed. Most of the time
before we will all have done the
greatest thing that we'll ever do in our
life the moment before we likely were
not that confident in our ability to do
it. It's just such a wild thing. And
throughout my career I've been trying to
land on like how do you address the
confidence piece with athletes all of
whom have been told their whole lives
got to be confident. Only the confident
athletes win. Well, they don't feel like
that most of the time when you're when
you're at a level where you are the one
of the best in the world and you got to
go up against the other best in the
world. Like nothing about that feels
feels good. So I just I differentiate
the notion of confidence which I see as
a very fleeting thing. It could change a
lot with belief. Belief is a very
foundational structured thing. When when
I say bet on yourself that's belief. So
with with athletes, I spent a lot of
time trying to distinguishing do you
believe versus do you feel confident?
>> You're an outdoors person. Did you fish
much growing up?
>> A little bit.
>> Imagine, let's imagine you you loved to
fish and there was like a lake somewhere
that you lived at and your grandfather
would take you out and
>> all those things are true by the way.
>> Okay. So put yourself back in this boat
with your grandfather and your
grandfather not only took you out to
fishing, he wanted to teach you the
craft of fishing. He wanted to teach you
the art. And so this place where he
would take you to go fish, he'd explain
exactly why and where at certain
different times of the day you'd want to
go to this part of the lake or you
wanted to go to this part of the lake or
you wanted to go to this part of the
lake. And there was one part of the lake
that he explained to you exactly why
this is where is the best chance you're
going to get a fish. And some days you
go out there and the water is crystal
clear and you can actually see the fish.
And so you throw your line out and you
wait.
Well, when you see the fish there, those
that's the day that you're confident
like, I see it. I feel it.
But some days the water's murky
and you can't see the fish, but you
throw your line out anyways because you
knew that exactly why. You knew what
your grandfather told you. You knew when
it it happened. And even though you
couldn't see them, you knew they were
there. That's belief. And athletes spend
too much time, oh, I can see it or I
can't see it. And that dictates their
sense of belief for themsel. But belief
is much more underlying and much more
consistent and takes a lot longer to
build and to also break down than just
the general notion of confidence.
Confidence in big moments, in pressure
moments,
>> the source of that confidence for most
people is the recency.
>> How do I feel right now? How was my last
time I was here? Like the recency piece
is Yeah. is the biggest thing. And
>> it's great when the recent stuff has
been great and you woke up with the full
night of sleep and you ate exactly what
you wanted to sleep. When you feel great
and warm up is great and then oh, I see
the fish. I'm going to throw my line.
But like most performance happens when
that water's murky. And so we have to
zoom out from just what's our source of
confidence or our belief in the moment.
Is it just the most recent things that
we're feeling or our last performance or
the warm-up I just had or how I'm
feeling in the moment? Or is it me
really really being very proactive with
building all the different sources of
confidence that I might be able to have
for myself? The term in the field right
now is called robust confidence. Robust
meaning it's very hard to break. It
withstands a lot. Robust confidence is
you don't take your confidence from a
single source. You take your confidence
from a variety of sources.
For athletes, this is your physical
performance. For athletes, this is the
mental the time they put in with the
mental side of their performance is a
source of confidence. For athletes, it's
the hours of self-care that they put in
away from their sport environment to
recover and to prepare. Most elite
athletes I've worked with who have been
the most successful
have nailed the self-care piece. They're
doing all the check boxes of what they
have to do both in recovery and
preparation away from their sport
environment. If they're a swimmer, it's
what they're doing in the training room.
It's what they're doing in their dorm
room at night. They're rolling out.
They're stretching. They're taking the
supplements. They're doing the
visualization. Like that self-care piece
for those elite athletes. Well, you
can't take that away.
No matter how I feel in warm-up does not
take all that stuff away. And I tell
athletes at the elite level, your job is
to build your confidence. That's your
job. Spend a lot of time knowing where
that confidence come from. And then in
competitive moments, your job is to
fight for it
>> and not allow it to be swayed by one
thing that happened more recently to us.
So robust confidence and having
confidence come from multiple sources,
those that we typically don't consider.
The type of feedback we're getting, this
type of social support we have are all
ways that might enable an athlete to not
put so much weight into this is how I
feel right now. This is how my last
performance was. Today's episode is
sponsored by David. David makes protein
bars unlike any I have ever encountered.
They have an amazing 28 grams of
protein, only 150 calories, and zero
grams of sugar. That's right, 28 grams
of protein and 75% of its calories come
from that protein. This is 50% higher
than the next closest protein bar.
Honestly, it's the best tasting bar I've
ever had in my life by a mile. And their
newest bar, the David Bronze Bar, tastes
incredible as well. While I often talk
about the importance of getting one gram
of protein per pound of body weight for
things like muscle health and recovery
and the promotion of lean body mass and
satiety, the reality of that is for most
people getting that one gram of protein
per pound of body weight is really
challenging. However, David makes that
easy. Their bars taste incredible. The
gold bar is packed with 28 grams of
protein with just 150 calories. And the
bronze bar has 20 grams of protein, also
with just 150 calories. I eat one almost
every single day and always have two or
three with me in my backpack when I'm
traveling. And I like literally mean
always. It probably sounds funny, but I
eat them as dessert all the time. When
you try them, you'll know exactly what I
mean. If you're interested in trying
these bars for yourself, you can go to
davidproin.com/perform.
Again, that's davidproin.com/perform.
This is akin to discipline versus
motivation. Motivation is a really bad
thing to use.
>> That's your confidence.
>> Maybe it's here. Maybe it's not.
>> And it is a drug beyond all drug when
you have it, right?
>> Feels great.
>> It feels great.
>> But then when you don't have it, you're
toast if you don't have
>> Exactly.
>> discipline. Right.
This is very similar to what I was going
to ask a second ago regarding
I believe you. I got to get better at
just not expecting comfort. Fine. I have
a almost identical question here. I
think it's going to be the same answer.
If I believe you, belief is more
effective than confidence here or even
robust confidence is
>> more effective. What actual things have
you used whether this is practices or
tools or strategies to help people gain
that
>> I believe you but now what do I actually
do to build this up
>> one of them is to make sure that we know
there's a distinction between feeling
confident and being nervous
the the underlying piece of the
performance anxiety and the being
nervous and to have those expectations
and pressure
>> if I put a harmon on you I couldn't tell
Right.
>> But you can
>> we have to make sure that we understand
those are two very different things. You
can be extremely nervous in the moment
and you can be extremely confident at
the same time.
And when I like one of my very first
meetings at Cal was with one of our
men's rowers and he was on the team the
previous year before I got there that
won the national championship and was in
the varsity boat that won the national
championship race and he talked about
being nervous and I said go back to last
June 1st the morning of the IRA final.
Talk me through that. He felt nauseous.
He couldn't eat. He super nervous. What
happened? Obi-Wan
like being able to piece together like
you can you can most certainly feel
nervous in the moment. You can most
certainly even at times
>> confuse that with the state of readiness
which you you really shouldn't do that.
But like the first piece of it is I can
be confident and I can be nervous at the
same time. And when you sort of make
that an understanding then the
confidence piece is a lot easier to hold
on to when we're feeling those nerves
when we're feeling that discomfort. that
that part absolutely has to has to be
done first. Otherwise, if we include the
same, you're going to be nervous
beforehand. You're going to be and you
could be nervous and you could be
confident at the same time. That's a big
thing. I also and you know different
athletes do it different ways but if
athletes can somehow in some form be
really proactive with writing down
things that they've done or experienced
that lead to confidence
and then in moments where they're they
forgot about those things they pull that
out right there was a an athlete at Cal
very successful athlete who kept on her
desk a confidence jar
and she'd go home and she'd just write
something down on a little piece of
paper and put it in. Something she did
well that day in practice or something
she accomplished she didn't think she
should or something she was disciplined
about when she didn't feel like it. She
just and then when she got these big
competitions she just poured that out
and start reading over them and it's
like we forget about those things
because the recency effect. I feel
stressed right now. Yeah. But look at
the months and months that you've done
with this work. I I do have different
athletes who sort of are amendable to
this kind of journal.
>> Yeah. I'll give a very very great
technique. It's called 321. And you can
spread it out however you want to spread
it out. But imagine you're a performer,
you're an athlete or in your job, Sunday
night for example. Three things that you
did well or that you are proud of or
that built confidence for you over the
last week.
Two things that you struggle with, fell
short on, messed up, you know, failed.
And then one focus moving forward. three
things you did well, two things you
messed up on. What's your focus moving
forward? But record them. And when you
do that long enough, you're going to
start to see trends. And if you do long
enough of the I'm going to really think
about the things that bring me
confidence.
What kind of car do you drive?
>> Me?
>> Yeah.
>> Uh Rivon truck.
>> A Rivon?
>> Yeah. If you and I are driving in the
Uber as we did here and a ri a Rivon
passes us, you would notice that and I
would not notice that.
>> Of course,
>> it's your truck. You're primed to see
that. I don't see it at all. But if a
Mazda CX-5 drives, especially if it's a
bright red color, I register for that
because that's what I'm looking for.
That's I associate something with that.
and athletes who spend a lot of time
reflecting on those sources of
confidence for themselves throughout a
long training cycle. It becomes more
like the Rivian. Oh, there it is. There
it is. There it is. Now, people who are
overly negative and beat themselves up,
that practice is not going to turn that
away in two weeks. You've got to do that
for a long time. You've got to be
committed to doing that for a long time
because your mindset took a long time.
It's not like the settings on a phone
where you can just change it. And now
all of a sudden now this message goes to
do not disturb our mindset. The settings
of our brain take a long time to to do.
So another part of building the
confidence is putting the time in to
find it on a pretty regular basis.
>> I would assume you're going to say
you prefer if not require this to be
physically written down rather than just
a mental exercise.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Got to write it down.
pretty much a renowned statement from
folks in your side of the world. You're
not just going to do a mental exercise.
It's got to be on a piece of paper
>> or on a phone and a note or some some
form. It's got to be
>> it's got to get out of your brain.
>> Yes.
>> The 321 is really I like what I like
about it is many things, but one of them
that popped up to me immediately was
first of all, you're acknowledging good
and bad.
>> Yeah.
>> But you're waiting good. You're doing
three, not two. I don't know if that was
in purpose or total accident, but that
seems even if someone is struggling with
confidence, you're you're going to spend
more time thinking about good than you
are bad, but you're going to acknowledge
both. And then again, I'm sure this is
all intentional. But the one is an
action. So even after you hit those
negatives, you walk from those negatives
with a step moving forward.
>> That's right.
>> Which is great. Like so good. The first
two parts is that three two are
reflective
and then the
one is the in is the intent.
>> The intent
>> that's moving forward from that.
>> And so what your car analogy was for
folks that maybe are not self-aware.
They don't have a lot of reflective
innate skills or practices is not
natural to them. By doing that you will
start to see those patterns of positive
or negative or whatever they happen to
be. Some people are already naturally
good at that stuff. Some people are, you
know, very dull in that sense, right?
It's like no connection to yourself.
>> But by doing this, you'll start to see
those patterns and then you'll start to
see things that are themes that are
popping up
>> right
>> over and over again. And so by doing
that, that can build that confidence
that can that could find that
confidence. Is that how you build the
belief or is that a different thing or
how do we get from that confidence to
the belief? Ultimately that will turn
into an underlying belief because one
thing that tends to happen then is that
those confidence pieces that we found
also then turn into forms of selft talk.
We now recite those things to ourselves.
We repeat those things to ourselves. And
what that's going to do then is it's
going to be more effective for us in the
moment to have that belief.
>> Um the reflection process when it comes
to belief is super important. You know,
I think sometimes athletes feel like
Sisphus pushing the rock up that giant
mountain every single day and they have
to kind of oh, I got to do it again. In
that moment, they could they could lose
those moments of joy and they can lose
those moments of things that are really
working well for them.
>> That um feedback that coaches often give
focus on the things that they need to do
differently. I think coaches do
reinforce the positive things, but a
coach's job is to point out
areas that an athlete can get better. So
they get that kind of source of I got to
focus on doing that better, do that
differently. But internally now they can
start focusing on some of the more
confident things.
>> You mentioned a tactic there of writing
these things down filling up a jar. So
when you're lost your confidence or your
whatever, you can pull it back up. What
about the opposite? Folks that are
overly confident.
>> I've heard people in my field say
they've never ever heard of an athlete
who's overconfident.
They just have never heard of it before.
>> They've never heard or they've never
really seen it. I don't believe
>> it's something misplaced or
>> Yeah. There's no such thing as too much
confidence.
>> What is that really then?
>> The way that I see it play out is you
start cutting corners.
>> Yep.
>> You start um this is when upsets happen.
>> Sure.
>> What's the opposite of underdog? When
someone is the expected winner of
something, they also prepare like that.
The favorite, they also prepare like
that. And that's where I believe
overconfidence plays out with I just
thought I had it and I didn't do the
things I needed to that got me here in
the first place. and that bit me in the
ass. And so now that could be that could
be considered on my mind a case of
someone being overconfident because they
in fact didn't do all the things they
needed to do. I think I would I would
want that person to be really
self-honest.
>> Mhm.
>> I don't want to necessarily have them be
less confident. I don't wouldn't go from
a place like that. But you need a you
need to be in a place of honesty and you
need to have people in your life who are
going to be able to tell you what you
need to hear. If you're thinking about
yourself, you being in that boat of I'm
I'm not gonna, you know, I'm not I'm not
gonna lack confidence, there are going
to be times where you need people who
you trust, maybe the people you run on
that list to say, you know, you're
actually not that good at that as you
thought you were.
>> Oh, I trust me, I got someone that my
house that does it every day and and do
that. Oh, yeah. That's a necessary
thing. Like I know you think that about
yourself. However,
um we all need that in our lives for
somebody who can point out like that
actually is more of a decrement than you
think it might be. And if you don't
change that, then it's going to come
back and and potentially bite you. The
reason I I think it's very rare to have
that happen is because I think most of
us come from a place of when we when we
perform, we do something about that we
really care about. And when we care
about something, we see the potential of
us not doing well as a threat. And that
threat is what leads to the anxiousness
for us. And that anxiousness is what's
going to potentially rattle our
confidence. And so I I think in most
very very high performance settings, I I
think it's probably rare to see someone
who's overconfident, so to speak.
>> Got it. How do you think about
confidence, belief versus resilience?
>> Well, they're they're different things,
right? I think you can probably be
resilient at times and not be terribly
confident, but you don't really have
much of a choice. I'm going to push
through this. I'm gonna
The piece with the resilience piece that
I think we forget about is the passion
piece. Like whether we're confident or
not in a moment, if we're if we're
dealing with something that we're
passionate about,
>> that passion is what's going to make us
resilience.
>> That's Angel Duck's great, you know, is
that we forget about it's not just
working hard through things. It's you
have passion for the goals that you're
pursuing. And the passion is there even
when the confidence is not there. So you
can be resilient in the presence of
pursuing that even when you're
experiencing setbacks and even when you
don't necessarily feel confident in the
moment to be able to do that. That's how
I kind of see those mental toughness.
So when I think about confidence, when I
think about belief as you're describing
them, I think, okay, my belief is there.
I built that. That's a long-term system
that you put into me. So now that's not
going to waver. confidence is going to
go up and down based upon things like if
I lack mental toughness, I might lose my
confidence. If I'm down in my score, if
I screwed something up, if I get
physically tired,
this I feel like this is how a lot of
people represent mental toughness. And
uh whether those are actually connected
or not or that's the right terminology,
I'm not exactly sure. So that be one be
great to hear that clarified. But is
that something that is underpinning this
wavering confidence or are those in fact
separate things as well? Mental
toughness generally is framed as a
person's ability to perform their best
under any circumstance.
And so you're getting into a little bit
about the resilience piece because I
need to be able to be my best when the
weather is not favorable or something
unexpected happens to me or something
happens with the equipment that I've
relied on and now I have to use a
different tennis racket or mental
toughness is one's ability to perform at
their best regardless of the conditions.
Now, confidence is obviously going to be
a big piece of that, but coping skills
is another big piece of the mental
toughness piece. Meaning, I wish
something was the way it was. It's not.
And what do I want to do with that? Part
of it is a level of acceptance. Like
some some of this stuff is just I can't
control it. I can't change it. So, I'm
going to just accept the circumstance
that I'm in. And when I accept it, it
takes a lot of the power off of it.
That's a form of coping tool. So in
those moments when we're dealing with
adversity, which is what we typically
associate with resilience, some of it
could be the confidence piece, but other
piece of it can be other coping tools
that we've learned
>> when we're experiencing that to be able
to perform while those things are
happening.
you mentioned earlier, I think the
emotion piece and I think when I think
of coping strategies and mental
toughness, I think the emotional
regulation piece is a a really really
really massive part of it and I think
this is maybe where that comes in. So
I'm dealing with something and something
occurs that registers into me some
emotion.
I think from a mental performance
perspective, a psychological
perspective, the emotional regulation
piece in performance environments is you
can't get away. If I were to use in the
sports that I work with one word that
describes a sport the most, I would say
emotional. Tennis is a more emotional
than anything else. I think it's why
people watch sports. I think it's why
people play sports. It's why if you
already knew the result of the NFC
Championship game, watching it would
mean something entirely different than
watching it without knowing.
>> I can't watch games ever like the
recorded games. I can't do it.
>> No chance.
>> There's nothing for you. There's no
what? There's no emotion with that. Why
not? Because you know the result of it.
So that's that that's going to come with
sports is the emotional piece. And in
the work that I do with athletes that
has changed a lot from I think earlier
in my career the term emotional control
and being able to control our emotions
was one of the kind of like prominent
ways of like oh well if you're nervous
then control that don't be nervous or if
you made a mistake and you're frustrated
then just don't be frustrated just
control that emotion. I think the
science behind it right now does not
look at it as a form of controlling
emotions so much as regulating ourselves
when we experience emotions.
Just like I mentioned about selft talk
about the danger of distinguishing
positive versus negative selft talk. I
also think what's really helpful when we
want to regulate our emotions is also
not see an emotion as being a positive
or negative thing. We generally, all of
us, well, first of all, most people if
they were asked to name emotions, they
could probably list about 10.
>> Yeah, sure.
>> There's hundreds.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> There's hundreds of emotions, right?
>> Remember once we're in the movie? I
could I could get that far. That's
>> or part two even. And so when we do
that, we tend to distinguish, oh, that's
a positive or a negative emotion. And
that's where we get into the whole
control thing is, well, if it's a
negative emotion, we can't have that.
Every emotion serves a purpose.
And when I'm experiencing an emotion, I
have to first be able to label what the
emotion is first. And then I have to
understand why that emotion exists. And
when I know why an emotion exists, I'm
not so worried about fighting it anymore
because I know it serves a purpose.
Okay? Great example is like, you know,
regret. You say something and it hurts
somebody and you realize that and then
you experience regret. Regret is not a
pleasant emotion to experience, but we
have it because
the next time we're in that environment,
we're a lot less likely to hurt the
person that we didn't intend to hurt. So
that's why we feel regret. And so when I
feel it, I know why I feel it. And I can
manage that response a little bit
better. So I think what's really
important with emotions, there's a great
recent book out called Dealing with
Feelings. I hate the title of it. Mark
Brackett is the author. or like I I
would have went with a different name,
but this this book about like it's never
the emotion that we experience that's
going to have any impact on our lives
whatsoever. It's how we respond to that.
It's what we do next.
>> The labeling of it and
>> very powerful thing. It's like someone
cuts you off and you get upset about it.
That's never what's going to change your
day. It's you flipping the guy off and
he flipping you off and now the two of
you stop and one of you gets out of the
car and next thing you know someone's in
jail. And that was the thing that ruined
your life, not the fact that you got
angry over it happening. So I do a lot
of like like the labeling piece with
athletes is like when you experience
that what emotion did you feel? Uh and
then we kind of get through why do you
think you experience that? And so the
emotional control piece is is pretty
huge. You can you can perform
successfully and and effectively in the
presence of any emotion.
The the big piece of it after the
labeling piece is to just say all right
that's what it is. And controlling it is
not going to do anything for you. often
is just okay, that's why I'm feeling
this. What do I want to do with that?
What's next for me? It's that next
what's next piece. So, I'm going to have
the reaction. It's going to last a few
seconds. Then I have to stop. I got to
take a breath for a moment. All right.
Now, what? Now, what do I want to do?
And then the emotion has no power
whatsoever. Now, when you're very
emotional environments and your coaches
emotional and the fans are emotional and
your teammates are emotional, that can
be difficult to do, but it actually
gives you a a massive massive power.
Another piece with the emotional piece
that's been really really I think
pronounced recently is this not notion
of how we experience emotions and the
presence of other people's emotions is
called co-regulation.
>> This similar to like mirror
>> mirror neurons or sort that at the
neurological level. Um if you were to
drink whiskey or wine it would taste
better when you did it with someone you
liked.
>> It would taste better. Movies are more
powerful when you watch them with people
you like versus when you're watching
them yourself. Music, when you listen to
music with other people is far more
emotional than when you listen to a song
by yourself. It's a great starting point
to understand co-regulation or what's
also referred to as emotional contagion.
Meaning what I'm experiencing
emotionally is very easily caught. And
when I work in very high pressure
situations with with which I do, I need
to know what emotion is that athlete
sitting in my office feeling and then
how do I want to co-regulate that?
Sometimes you use the phrase a mirror. I
think you were referring to mirror
neurons.
>> Yeah, exactly. Yeah.
>> Sometimes I want to match that person's
emotion because it validates it and I
need I need to know if they're feeling
sad when should I also have a reaction
that's sad? what what does that help
them to do? I also need to know maybe
when I need to exhibit a different
emotion for them. They're feeling really
really afraid of something. Maybe I need
to bump up the confidence piece or the
excitement piece or something. So, the
co regulation thing is a massive thing
when it comes to human relationships.
Coaches have a massive responsibility
with the co-regulation piece in
competitive sports because number one,
they're the adult in the room literally.
>> Yep.
um they've been there, they've done that
usually and they walk into a locker room
and locker rooms are very emotional
places and the first thing a coach needs
to do is read the room. It's halftime.
We're down two goals. Is the team not
taking it seriously? Are they too light?
If that's the case, they need to up the
intensity
to bring focus in the players. the
players are too low, they're too
negative with each other. The coach is
going to need to do something that's a
lot more positive in that moment to kind
of co-regulate that environment. It's a
massive tool in places of work like just
seeing a co-worker, seeing your spouse
exhibit some emotion and knowing what
you can do in that moment to help them
regulate that an emotion a little bit
better, whether it be mirroring that
emotion with them or trying to counter
that emotion with itself. And I think
that's the new frontier of emotion
regulation because we work, humans work
in relationship to each other. That
co-regulation piece is a very exciting
new kind of area that that I'm
interested in.
>> I'm going to ask you for
you to put your coaching hat on and I'm
going to give you a scenario and I want
you to coach me through this.
>> Okay?
>> And this scenario is going to make your
stomach turn.
>> Awesome. Uh yesterday the NFC
Championship game
and there was a play with one of the
players uh Tariq Woolen the corner and
uh the end of the game the Seahawks his
team got a a big stop
almost surely we're going to win the
game because of this. after the play is
over.
>> He's basically on the other team's
bench,
>> trash talking, gets a flag, so the Rams
get to keep the ball and the game ends
up coming out of the wire because of it.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, right after that flag happened,
the very next play, the Rams throw a
pass right at him.
>> They score a touchdown on him. So, you
went from giving the team the ball back
to giving them seven points. The entire
stadium went from about 115 dB positive
>> y
>> to booing and the whole planet I'm sure
in Reek Woolen's brain was hating him in
that moment.
>> Mhm.
>> If you were Reek himself
and then I want to ask you if you were a
coach or someone on the sidelines. I
have no idea what happened. Turns out
the Seahawks still won. Great. That's
amazing. That's the most important part
of the story. Seahawks still won the
game after that flag. Well, you all can
hopefully empathize with what he was
feeling. You know was mad at you. His
team's literally yelling at him. We saw
images of his team there and you don't
know what they're saying. They could
have been saying, "You're the man. We
love you." Like, you don't know that
they're saying negative stuff to him.
>> Sure.
>> But the most predictable thing ever on
that next play was like, "They're going
to go right at this guy." And now in
fairness, the guy that scored a
touchdown on him is one of the best
players in the whole league. So that
could happen on any play. So I don't
even know if what I'm trying to walk
away from is the assumption that this
was all negative. I don't know.
>> Sure. But what would you have said after
that flag knowing
something inside's going to be happening
right now? You just let the team down on
a really bad decision. What are their
phrases? Are there sayings if you were
Reek himself in that second person,
Reek? What What kind of things would you
be saying to yourself? And then as a
coach would be my second question.
>> Number one, move on. The game's not
over. His doing that was a great
indication that he was thinking ahead
and that he was using his emotional
response to predict the future and to
rub it in and to do whatever it is that
that he wanted to do.
>> So after the play, he thought the game
basically was over and he he let he
probably let himself go too far.
>> Yes. That he had the emotional reaction
of being excited about it. His response
then was that's right. And then his
response was to do what led to that
occurring.
>> In all fairness, I did not watch that
play. I had a very hard time watching
most of that game.
>> We'll leave out why. We'll leave out
why.
>> I'm a big Niners fan and yeah, I was
still reeling from that.
>> You're at a 15-year joke, friends.
>> In the moment, the most important thing
for him, cuz he has to go go back on the
on the field.
>> Yeah. Like the very next play.
>> Not to judge him, not to shame him, not
to do whatever. It's move on. We're in
the game. Next play. That's the only
thing I could have ever said to that guy
in that moment. It's not to try and
counsel him out of it. It's not to get
him to apologize. Nothing. But
>> so his selft talk should have been reek.
That didn't matter. Like next, what's
the next step?
>> Make a stop. We got to make a stop. It's
the only thing that I'm trying to do is
to get him to come back to the present
moment.
>> Now, he's gonna probably I don't know
what his next step is going to be with
the team or I don't know what, but he's
going to have to learn from that. But in
that particular moment right now, I
needed to come back to the now and like
you got to go make a stop right now.
That's enough. before we go on to the
coach on the couch. My brother said he's
going to make a mistake trying to make
up for that. So you have this one thing
of like lack lack of confidence right
there
>> and then you have the probably what many
competitors would do would be to go too
far
>> of course
>> and what they end up doing is they run a
>> what's called the double route basically
like fake one way then go the other
because he was being so aggressive to
make the play.
>> Yeah.
>> Move on to the next play would makes
sense to me that that would stop the
negative selft talk. Huh?
>> How do you make sure you don't press and
go too far, right? How do you stay
present in the next play without being
like, "You have to make up for this
right now."
>> So, he needs to be directed. He's got to
regulate his physiology in the moment
immediately. Take a deep breath first.
Separate yourself from the situation.
Walk back to the defensive huddle. When
you're doing that, you've got to
downregulate as much as you possibly
can. Breathe. Come on. Come down. Come
down. Come down. Get focused so that he
can be engaged and ready to make the
stop on the next play. I think it was
very smart what the Rams do to target
him because that
>> the biggest non-surprise ever. You go
right at him, right?
>> Yep. So, just in that moment, I we got
to get this guy to to be quickly
downregulated and get back and refocus
in the moment. That's the only thing
that matters in that moment. We can't
change the situation. He can't undo what
he did. He can't apologize for that
moment. He's got to go back there and
perform at that. The problem is is that
that lack of him being able to regulate
that spiral for him.
>> Yeah. And then it it turned into him
probably doing what you said, which is
to then try to now have to prove and do
too much. And you know,
>> do you tell yourself again using your
second like if you hear him, do you say,
"Reek, just do your job. Get back here.
Don't worry about it, but just do your
job.
>> It's over. What's next? We got to make a
stop.
>> Yep.
>> I don't need to do too much. I don't
need to do too little."
>> Right here.
>> Mhm.
>> Besides a down regulation breath.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Are there any other physical things they
can do? I'm thinking of athletes I know
sometimes will have a they'll wear a
piece of jewelry or they'll well wear
something on their body that is kind of
their their home base.
>> Mhm.
>> Things like that that people can try as
as a way to get back when I just like
can't catch my breath. I can't calm my
bra. Like I know what I'm supposed to be
doing, Dr. Wema, but like it's not
working. I'm freaking out right now.
>> You ever seen George KD's tattoo on his
forearm?
>> No.
>> He has a little reset button.
>> No kidding. something something like
that that he learned when he was in
college that he needed to like push tap
his arm and that was his way of
resetting now I'm coming right back to
my present moment my center so he has a
a physical thing he'll actually touch
himself on and a tattoo of it
>> huh yeah I haven't seen it in person
I've heard him talking about it before
>> can that be anything is there specific
stuff that has to be does it matter at
all what that tactical thing is
>> when I work with tennis players and they
have that little um what do they call it
a
>> little eye in the racket
>> but they'll either on that piece of it
or on the wrap of their handle. They'll
write something down.
>> One of the teams I was working with last
year, there was a player who used to in
motions go and he get he get picked on
by their team. They would purposely
target him to get him out in in the red.
Right.
>> This is a really common thing, by the
way, for people if if you don't know pro
sports. That is a really highly coached
thing.
>> Yeah.
>> Is like a an intentional playbook thing
that will be done to go after people
like that. and we had to figure out a
way for him to be able to use what we
were the the phrases we were using in my
office to go out on the field when it
was occurring. And so he would put taper
on his
wrist and I'm not going to say he wrote
it, but then he would he would look at
that a lot.
>> So it can be a phrase, it can be a
reminder, it can be a it doesn't matter
what it is cuz because you could write
reset, the word reset, and it wouldn't
matter for any athlete and it matters
for George. Like it the word is totally
independent for the person, right? And
then if I'm one of his teammates and I
go over and I put my hand on his
shoulders and I say, "Look me in the
eyes." Like that is a grounding thing,
that's co-regulation at its greatest, I
think, is when you look me in the eyes
and say, "Right here, take a breath with
me. Let's go. Make a stop." Like that's
a super super powerful thing.
>> So if second part then would have been
if you were his coach or teammate,
that's what you'd have done
>> in that moment. Yeah. In that moment,
>> you know what's happening with him. He
feels horrible about it.
>> Yeah. And he's got to come back out
there and he's got to perform.
>> Yeah. When I work with a team, I try to
create common language so that it's a
very powerful concept and it's either a
visual or some very short term that
represents what that concept is so that
everybody is in the same page with it.
And our I try to be careful about using
examples that people can gain who I'm
talking about, but one of the teams that
I work with, our men's soccer team was
in the ACC playoffs last year and we
were in the lead on the road against a
much higher ranked team and towards the
end of the game, one of the players in
their team took out one of our guys with
a very obviously illegal tackle meant to
hurt the kid.
>> And we did it for a reason, so that we
would respond. we would react, right?
And everybody from the coaches, the
bench, the people on the field at the
same time said the exact same thing to
each other
>> and it's just like we all got it. Like
that's the value of being able to have a
unified
powerful messaging that like all of us,
we all could look each other eyes and
just say one thing and we got it. Not
going to affect us. We're right here,
right? So I try to I try to help teams
create that sort of communication in
that language.
>> These would qualify as your differences
between emotional control versus
emotional regulation.
>> I think so. Yeah. Yep.
>> I guess is the regulation piece.
>> What do we do now?
>> Right. Rather than controlling it as a
way of thinking about don't let it get
out of
>> Right. Right. Right. Yeah.
>> Don't let it move or hold it.
>> No. No. Just what do we what's next?
>> How do we bring it back to this this
midline?
>> Mhm.
Today's episode is sponsored by Element.
Element is an electrolyte drink that has
an ideal electrolyte ratio of sodium,
potassium, and magnesium, but no sugar.
Hydration is critical to performance,
both physical and mental. And countless
studies have shown that even a slight
degree of dehydration, even as small as
1%, can lead to decreases in physical
output and mental performance. We also
know that electrolytes are critical to
proper hydration, which I've been
harping on for years. But you can't do
that. proper hydration by only drinking
water, especially if you sweat a lot.
You need to get the right amount of
electrolytes in the right ratios. And
that's why I'm a huge fan of Element. In
fact, many of you might remember that I
featured Element in my YouTube series on
hydration nearly 6 years ago. I featured
Element in these videos because their
blend of a,000 milligs of sodium, 200
milligs of potassium, and 60 milligs of
magnesium really is unique and different
than any other electrolyte on the
market. and it has great scientific
support. I use Element on nearly a daily
basis, especially when I'm doing really
hard training in the heat and I'm
sweating a lot. If you'd like to try
Element, you can go to
drinklnt.com/perform
to claim a free element sample pack with
the purchase of any element drink mix.
Again, that's drinklmnt.com/perform
to claim a free sample pack. I know
you've worked with some UFC fighters.
many of, you know, we've been fortunate
to share some clients in the past. I
think this is a really good example
because in the UFC, you fight for five
minutes and you have one minute. In
between rounds, you need three or five
rounds. You don't have 90 minutes. You
don't have two and a half hours. You
don't have timeouts. You don't So, as a
coach, you can either scream during the
fight, which is what they do, or you
have
realistically 30 to 40 seconds to coach.
>> Yeah. really tough thing. A friend of
mine, Sean Ali, I've known a long time.
His coach, Tim Welch, is one of the best
in the world. I think at the coaching in
between the rounds, he comes in the
round. Tim and Brandon, his other coach,
the first, I don't know, 10 seconds,
it's just be right here. I actually
think that's the phrase they use. I
can't remember exactly, but it's like,
be right here.
>> Be right here. They don't even actually
because a lot of coaches will say things
like, "Take a deep breath. Take a deep
breath." do that. But they actually like
almost gone to the second step already,
which is just like because Sean is so
trained on be right here also means
>> exactly
>> breathe, right? He doesn't say anything
more. Then he has a couple of points he
gets to and gets the next. I think we've
already covered that with what you just
said of why you would do that. My
question on this would be
when you see a UFC fight,
you'll see a couple of different styles
of coaching in the corner. One is a very
tactical. Hey, he's doing ABC. We want
to run this play, right? This exact
thing or do this move next. And the
other is just simply none of that.
>> And it's literally the slap in the face.
The
you'll see criticism
>> from fans because you're like, man, he
didn't do anything to he didn't need a
and then the other criticism is like he
didn't even tell him what to do. He just
hyped him up. I think it's foolish to
say one of those is there's a time and a
place where it's like you don't need
anything technical right now. You just
need there.
>> What is the time and the place for
either one? How do I know as that corner
person and if you're not coaching UFC
fighters, I get it. There's like 12 of
you.
>> This is the same thing though as if you
are and picture yourself in any
situation you're in, right? How am I
leading my children? How am I leading my
whatever through really intense
situation where pressure is on the line.
We got to move quickly. I don't know if
you can give us any direct answers here,
but how do I even know when I need to
just give the raw raw and I don't worry
about technical or the opposite or I
need to blend both? You kind of brought
this up earlier. If you are a coach, you
should already know in that moment what
that athlete needs and you could be
having 20 athletes you coach and every
single one of them might need something
different. That's your first job.
Whether it be flat out in situations
like this, what do you need from me?
That conversation is massively important
because the athlete will tell you what
they need.
>> So, this is coaching to the athlete
rather than coaching to your coaching
style.
>> 100%. 100%. The best coaches are the
ones that can adapt to what that
particular athlete needs. So, you should
know going into it exactly what that
athlete needs or wants. And needing and
wanting are different. Sometimes an
athlete wants something and the
conversation well in advance of it is I
think you also need this. The athlete
might want to say, "Just let me breathe
for a minute." And the coach might need
to say, "I'm here to give you one or two
things that I want you to think about
going into the next round. I'll do that
in the best way to help you." So, that's
got to be known before the so that now
the coach isn't making a decision when
the coach is emotional.
>> You'll be stunned that that conversation
never happens.
>> It has to happen.
>> It never happens.
>> The coach is a performer in that moment
and the coach is emotional and the coach
is on edge. And depending on how the
fighter is doing, that coach is feeling
the same way. And now if you go in there
with
>> sometimes worse I'm telling you right
now coaching those people
>> for sure.
>> Oh, it's horrible.
>> That should be something that is known
before that moment occurs. You have to
take into consideration the fact that in
that fiveminute round
that fighter's mind is racing at all
times. They're taking in so much
information and in that minute they have
they can't be getting too much more of
that. They have to have a place where
they can just detach and let that sort
of mental fatigue clear out a little bit
before they're the coach is probably
going to be able to say anything that
they're actually going to register and
remember going out there. I think you
have to take that into account. Whatever
you say needs to be simple and it
shouldn't be anything new. And I think I
think going into it having phrases that
you can use that you can that the
athlete already knows what it means. I
work with our tennis teams and our
stands at Cal are right over the courts.
It's a dream of my role. So, I could sit
right literally right over the player
and see their routines and are they
doing the breathing and have they gone
to the towel and what is the coach
feedback to them? If it's doubles, I get
to hear the doubles. I was perfect. I
could be in their mind in that moment. I
know exactly what it is they're doing.
But I can also then hear the coach's
feedback and man, our head coach is
amazing at that piece of it. He knows
exactly what that athlete might need to
hear in that moment. And he'll say
something like, "Go fishing." This is
not the same reference of the fishing
example I gave earlier. The coach used
to go fishing when he in his mind when
he was a player himself at the elite
level because he was stressed and
between points he would just close his
eyes and go to the lake and just like a
for a moment of down regulation is I'm
going fishing for just a moment. So
they'll use that as an example that
phrase go fishing. They know exactly
what it means. They've heard it before.
It's simple and it allows them to do
whatever they might want with that.
That's the approach I think I would take
in that situation in that minute as a
coach. Yeah. Yeah. Are you familiar with
the uh I think it was Joe Montana with
the Super Bowl story.
>> Mhm.
>> Is it was it Joe?
>> It was Joe Montana. Are you talking
about John Candy?
>> Uh no. In the stands.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Tell that.
>> Okay. So, it's the 1989 Super Bowl. The
49ers are playing against the Bengals.
The Niners are down by three points.
They have 92 yards to drive. And I
believe there was I don't know a couple
minutes on the clock.
>> Uh maybe less. Yeah. Very very end of
the game. Super Bowl. And so imagine now
the quarterback having a conversation
with the head coach in the sideline
because they didn't have the in-ear
microphones and then the team is all
huddled up and everyone in the huddle is
tighter as tight as can be and they're
in the end zone because that's where
they're starting on that side of the
field and Joe Montana walks out and he
sees the state that those guys he sees
their eyes like they're in the moment
but they're too much in the moment and
he goes look guys and he pointed the
stains like there's John Candy. Can you
believe John Candy's here? What the what
the offensive lineman has said is it
took their whole tension and just melted
it in a moment. Like number one, oh,
there's John Candy. Number two,
that's our quarterback.
He's not throttled at all. Let's
win this game. Like that moment of him
to be able to say something so
unexpected and composed like, "Hey,
there's John Candy, guys. Let's go win
this game." Like that one phrase just
changed everything. It's remarkable.
>> Yeah. Showing the rest of the team. Yes.
This is a big moment of course,
>> but I'm still able to have peripheral
senses. I'm in the moment. I'm right
here.
>> I do want to make a comment on that
about coaching when you say that that's
probably not a conversation coaches can
have. Coaching is a performance. And I
think often coaches think of themselves
as atmost coaches were athletes
themselves, at least the sports I work
with. And coaches need that performance
support as well. And for them to be able
to know that that conversation needs to
exist prior to that moment is something
that they can be taught and something
they can get a lot better at.
I feel like in my personal experience, I
know more coaches that have hired or
utilize sports psychologists or uh
mental performance coaches than I know
players.
I've never heard anybody talk about
that.
I think the general audience and fans do
not realize what percentage of coaches
because this is not different or this is
different rather than a coach taking a
leadership course taking a coaching
course which is how do I get more out of
my athletes. What you're referring to is
the coaches themselves wanting to get
more out of themselves. So what stuff
have you been doing recently?
We'll call it coaches but again this is
leadership. This is could also just be
you leading your kids. It doesn't
matter, right? How do you make sure your
emotional control versus regulation is
in the right spot? And is it maybe any
different than anything we've said
before that the exact same tools apply?
>> Every mental skill that I might teach an
athlete or skill that you might teach an
athlete, a performer can be utilized by
all those examples of the people you
just mentioned. every single one of them
visualizing whether it be visualizing
and the selft talk piece and the emotion
regulation everything we just talked
about
>> having a home base and yes bringing
themselves back down
>> all those things the interesting thing
about coaches and this is coaches in my
experience particularly working in
Olympic sports there's interesting
research on what's referred to as the
super elite athlete what distinguishes
between an elite athlete and a non-
elite athlete it's so much
>> y
>> but what distinguishes between the super
elite and the elite that's an
interesting and there's been a lot of
similar ities and one of those is, you
know, the super elite athlete
feels like they need to win more than
they want to win. They have to win.
Their life is over if they don't win.
And the perfectionistic tendencies that
they have, and that's very, very common
for the super elite athlete, many of
whom become coaches. And I could tell
you a number of coaches who I work with
or have worked with who came from the
super elite and now they're in the
coaching role. and all those traits that
they took to their performance that were
probably traits that could have cost
them, they initiate on their athletes.
And so they need to really really be
aware of when they're bringing that to
athletes who are probably nowhere near
as capable and talented and as
accomplished as they were. So, um,
number one, I think people don't realize
that most coaches are under more stress
and pressure than most athletes are. And
I think we tend to focus on the
performer, but it's the man or woman in
the sideline who's calling the plays who
probably is feeling a lot more of it.
And they have to be clear in those
moments and not emotional in those
moments. And yet all eyes fall on them
and it's expect of them. So working with
coaches is such a really really
important piece of what I do and what I
like to do. Number one, it's the hardest
part of my job and it's also my favorite
part of my job to be quite frank.
Coaches are can be very difficult to
work with, but they can also be like
super rewarding and fun to work with as
well.
>> You mentioned earlier being able to come
into a room and identify if they need
the energy or the tactics.
>> I imagine this is one of the things you
spend your time on. How do you help
those coaches learn that
>> after the fact?
>> Ah, I see. Reflection.
>> So, like, you know, if you're going to
give a coach advice, you better really
be trusted or you better be a total
stranger. I think those are the only two
people that a coach is going to listen
to. Like, oh, you said this. I don't
think they're going to listen to anybody
in between. And so, I I think part of my
job is to observe, evaluate. I take my
notebook and I'm very aware of maybe a
coach says something in the locker room
that I think I knew the intent of. And
then later, I'll say like, you mentioned
this in the locker room. I think this is
may have it came off. And they want to
hear that, I think, because often either
they didn't intend for it to be that way
or they intended it. And I said, "I
don't think it was the right approach."
And coaches want to hear that. They need
to hear that, but you got to be really
careful with how it is that you that you
phrase that. And I'm always going to
call out the things that they said that
were really, really good because, man,
coaches put on a master class of
leadership and very emotional moments.
And the things that coaches say in those
moments are just brilliant. I'll write
them down and I'll make sure afterwards
I'll say, "Man, when you said that, I
had to write that down. It was that
good." They need that reinforcement of
the things that they say that I think
really landed well to co-regulate the
group or to really focus the group or
how they gave critical feedback to an
athlete. They need to hear the things
they said that I think were really,
really powerful, were really, really
effective for them, coupled with the
things that I don't think they really
knew how that probably landed at the
time. And I think it's part of my job to
mention, look, you said this to the
group. I think this is how that was
taken. I think maybe think about it
differently next time we're in that
situation or something.
>> How do you personally create buyin
with that? I'll just assume head coach.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm hearing that right now thinking, I'm
coaching these people. All the pressure
is on me. If I win or lose, I'm getting
fired and I'm going to let some guy sit
in the corner with a notebook.
>> Notebook. Uh-huh.
>> That sounds like every coach saying,
"Hell
>> no."
>> Exactly.
>> How do you get to that spot?
>> You put the work in. You show up. You
sit in the coach's launch in the middle
of a rain and wind and you suffer with
them. And you sit there with them when
they've experienced their greatest uh
success and you sit with them when
they've experienced their greatest
failure. And you it takes time to build
that. We cannot do this work from our
offices. I don't know what kind of
picture people have in their mind of
like mental performance people or
psychologists who work with teams.
>> Can I tell you the picture, please?
>> Here's my picture.
>> I got a guy freaking out in the team.
Can't handle his I got to get a
sports psych in here. The only person
that needs it is the person who's
>> exactly
>> tanking in the big game. If I were to
picture
>> most of the field, that's what they
think sports psychology is. And then
that person either goes to an office,
>> Yep.
>> or sits on a Zoom caller, phone call.
>> They're not in the moment when it
happened. They didn't hear the feedback
the coach gave them. They're not getting
the hail pour down around on them.
They're not in the locker room after a
loss when everyone's crying, they're
crying with them. Like, you have to be
there and you have to be there through
all of it. And you have to admit when
you when something was on you. I mean,
with the with the coach last year of a
group, I said that was a mental loss and
that's on me. That's totally on me. And
I'll be the first to say to your ad,
your sport admin or anybody else, that
was a mental loss and that should not
have happened on my watch and it's not
going to happen again on my watch
because I'll make mistakes. I'll
underestimate things as well, of course,
>> and I'll hold on to that for years
afterwards. if I'm willing to be there
with them and I'm willing to be there
for the good and the bad and to make my
own mistakes and like learn with them.
And I think that that has to be there in
order for a coach to be able to let
someone sit there with a notebook in the
locker room.
>> We probably should have started the
conversation off with this, but this is
the difference between
what you guys are now calling mental
performance coaches and mental health,
>> right?
>> This is sports psychology versus
psychology or psychiatry.
It is this aspect of you're still
dealing with human emotions.
>> Yeah.
>> But it's an entirely different thing.
This is not just first of all, not
disease per se. And it's not just simply
I'm upset because this thing happened.
>> Yeah.
>> This is as active coaching
>> Yep.
>> as we could possibly get. And so when I
when I've had I'll say ownership and GM
groups of major sport teams ask me about
this aspect. Yeah. My reaction is, it's
funny you said earlier, but I always say
go all or go out.
>> Uhhuh.
>> Because if you're just hiring a
consultant here and there
>> who's in their office,
>> just just get out of like get them out
of here. If you if you're going to do
this, they should be a full staff
member.
>> Like you would hire a strength and
conditioning coach who's just like
sending programs.
>> They would never work. You would never
do that with a physical therapist.
>> Yeah.
>> You you want them in the building for a
reason. So if you're going to try to
work on this aspect, which Yeah. I don't
know. sports a real thing.
Still a little on the soft side for you.
>> Very soft science for me. I don't know
how you do this because if not, what
you're dealing with is with it's just
psychologist and fine. You want to send
them to an office twice a week and they
want to do talk therapy or whatever
amazing stuff they're doing. And you do
need that plenty of times. Loads of
athletes are humans too. They have
everything else going on. But this is
not that. What you're talking about is
really improving the quality of as many
interactions
as you can in practice, in the game, and
using what we've learned from clinical
and traditional psychology.
>> But in the sense of
excellence,
>> yeah,
>> performance,
>> performance, I guess, is one way to say
it.
>> It's embedded. My role in what I do in
being effective is to be embedded with
the team, be part of that team.
>> And then, you know, the services that we
provide at Cal, there's four full-time
mental performance consultants. No one
else in the country is doing this at the
collegiate level.
>> Four of them.
>> Four full-time.
>> Wow. That's how bad of your job you are.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> 30 teams.
>> I'm so bad they need four bad ones.
>> Four of you guys. And so we are
available for one-on- ones where the
student athletes can come into our
offices. That's where that type of work
takes place and then they can The
greatest thing about that is like I'm
also at practices. So I'm at practice in
the morning. This coach says something
to this athlete. The athlete comes in
and mentions it and then I get the
context
>> and I could say and you know the truth.
>> I was there well it did happen but
here's how I took that like it's good to
have a different perspective of it.
>> We're traveling. We're on the we're on
the benches with the coaches at games.
who are walking with the coach to the
locker room to help them process. Okay,
couple things that you might consider or
what what should I say or you know like
that's embedded work that's like fully
servicing our our coaches, our athletes,
our support staff, that sort of thing.
That's the way this field needs to work.
Bio feedback. I know you've used this a
lot. You're the first person I saw use
it many, many, many years ago. I've seen
you use it with professional athletes a
bunch of different realms. And why I
gravitated towards it was because I saw
the first connecting piece between
psychology and physiology. I think
sports psychology probably in the
beginning focused a lot on just like
managing your nerves. You're feeling
you're feeling nervous. What do you want
to do about it? What are some techniques
that you can use to kind of compose
yourself? We might refer to
downregulate. Now bio feedback was
probably one of the first ways that
people could actually demonstrate okay
if I'm going to tell you to breathe a
certain way you need to know why it's
not it's not good enough for me just to
say do this and this what happens
>> I think this is what caught me up right
>> yeah I want you to see it
>> okay I use BOF feedback in my office and
just last week I had a athlete come in
there and was just talking about like I
know I'm ready but I just don't like
that feeling before a race. I just I
just don't like that feeling and I I I
feel like my mind's starting to race a
little bit and I feel like things are
starting to tight tighten up and had a
great warm-up and then that period of
time from the warm-up to my event is it
just I got I needed to do something. I
was like I got something for you. So,
one of the bio feedback um programs that
we use is uh HRV
and we do breathing techniques. And so,
what I'll do is I'll have an athlete and
I'll I'll have them hooked up to the to
the BOF feedback and I'll just take a
moment to say, "Okay, now look at this
is your heart rate and this is what
you're seeing on the screen and
everything." And I'm going to just talk
for we're going to nerd out on this.
Athletes at Cal love to nerd out on
anything. I love it about these
athletes. Love to nerd out,
>> right? Yeah. So, okay, I'm going to let
this run now. I'm going to kind of talk
about what's happening. I'm going to
talk about the sympathetic. I'm going to
talk about the parasympathetic. I'm
going to talk about why athletes are so
good with the with the
>> I know what you're doing right now.
You're devious. You're a devious man.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. And I'm, you know, and then
>> and then I I like to I've got a
whiteboard and I like to kind of show
like all right, what what's happening
and why why is it that we extend our
exhale? What happens when we exhale with
our heart rate, for example? and what
are we looking for between the
sympathetic parasympathetic and and then
I'll like I'll say look at your heart
rate pattern there and I'll look at the
whiteboard and what if we were to be in
a state of coherence the balance between
the sympathetic and parasympathetic and
what if your heart rate pattern did this
and I draw it on the whiteboard and they
saw nothing like that on the screen
before at all I was like all right so
close your eyes for a moment and we're
going to take a few breaths I'm going to
talk you through and close your eyes and
I record on the time stamp on the BOF
feedback where this occurred and I talk
them through the breathing technique
that I wanted to use in um right before
their competition. I said, "Open your
eyes." And they're they just freeze
because what they're seeing on the
screen is exactly what I wrote on the
whiteboard.
And that's a powerful moment for them to
understand, okay, this is what's
happening. This is what to do when it's
happening. And then this is what's going
to happen. And then the big thing is
then when this happens then what? And so
now they know all that stuff. They
haven't seen anything yet. They open
their eyes and then boom, there it is.
And like it's a they need that in a
competitive moment for that belief. Like
when I'm doing the breathing right now,
even if I don't feel it doing anything
different, I'm going fishing. You know
why? Because I saw it. And then I do a
session with them where it's it's
testing if they can do it without
getting the immediate feedback. But then
you show them what's actually happening
later. It's like there's the fishing.
That's where you want to throw your
line. That's what's happening if you
just take a moment to compose yourself,
to control your breathing. That's all
you got to do in that moment. You don't
have to change anything else.
Everything's going to stay the same. But
just right now when you're feeling that,
this is all you got to do is simple.
Just slow things down. Let's just do
this for a moment. And now they know
exactly what's going to happen. And that
could actually be a super super powerful
tool.
It's not just I'm feeling tight. I want
to do something to I don't like the word
relax. That's not what we're getting at
to downregulate or to be more composed.
It's why and what's happening when I do
it. And that can be a really super
powerful thing.
>> I covered a lot of details of HRV
uh in a previous episode in a previous
>> the whole thing.
>> Okay, we can link that in the show notes
if you want more details. So, we'll skip
some of that now. But
what you're really saying here is I am
showing you how you can have cognitive
control over something like your heart
rate as a proxy of your overall
psychological state. So you're going
from psychology to physiology to go
right back to psychology. And by showing
these athletes this on the screen for
people like me, it becomes undeniable
now
>> because it's not just like do you feel
more calm? Do you feel more alert or
whatever it do? We're saying look at
these electrical signals in your heart
or your brain
>> and they're matched. And so when you
said you drew it on the whiteboard, you
were drawing what you wanted their heart
rate to be, gave them no instructions
about that,
>> had them close their eyes, they did this
thing and they came back and saw their
heart rate was exactly what you wanted
to be.
>> You did not you were not telling them
hold for three, exhale for two. None of
that was occurring, right? So to be
really clear because I know people are
going to hammer us in the questions
about this one. What was the breathing
protocol you gave them? Is this the same
for everybody? Does that part even
matter?
>> We test different ones, but the the
foundation for it and the basis for it
is roughly a 10-second breath cycle from
start to finish roughly.
>> Five in, five out.
>> Uh four in, six out.
>> Four in, six out. A little bit of
extended exhale to help kind of bring
back down.
>> Brings the brings the heart rate.
>> And why four
to six? Why 10 seconds? Why not longer?
Where did that number come from?
>> Well, that's that's what they found to
have the greatest impact on coherence on
HRV coherence. That's what they've they
tested a lot of different ways of doing
it.
>> Walk me through what what's HRV
coherence and why does that matter?
What's what's a rough
>> coherence is the balance between the
sympathetic and this parasympathetic
nervous system. And so we can look at
two things. We can look at the pattern.
Is it consistent in it regulating up and
regulating down? And we can also look at
the the distance between the peak and
the valley of that cycle. And that gives
us an indication of how strong that is.
And I want to make sure that it's not
about us or me proving anything to the
athletes. It's about here's a tool and
this is what happens
if you use this tool or even attempt to
use this tool. This is what's happening
and if this happens then this is what's
going to happen with respect to
performance or how you feel. And that's
a really really important piece of that
thing. So that that four and six out is
a way that we found has been the way to
regulate that coherence between the
sympathetic and nervous system in a most
balanced way.
>> Somewhere between four and 6 seconds is
probably what you'll find most people's
resonance breathing.
>> Yeah.
>> Frequency at I'm generally 7 and 1 half
to eight.
>> Yeah.
>> Mine's a lot higher. Doesn't mean
positive or negative or anything. It's
there.
>> Have you seen the same thing? Most
people like between four and six seconds
is that line up.
>> Yeah. And we have a we have a program
where we can adjust it and we can see
what And so they could actually follow
this dot and as long as it's going up
they breathe in and as long as it's
going up they they don't have to brea
they don't have to count to do it. And
that's where we can kind of find out
okay this seems to be like the pattern
that works best for you but we don't
want to rely on them seeing that in the
competitive environment. So we turn it
into accounting. Right. The first time I
saw you do it was I think there was a
computer program you used where I think
it was just to pull socks on somebody or
a heart rate monitor
>> and the only instructions you gave this
person was there was a screen and it was
a picture of some landscape in black and
white.
>> Mhm.
>> And all you said was something like make
the screen get color.
>> Yeah.
>> And I think and please fill me in if I
was wrong here. What was happening was
the software program was interpreting
when the either the heart rate was lower
or the HRV was higher, it would bring
more screens on the color.
>> Mhm.
>> Or color on the screens. And then if it
did the opposite, it would start getting
black and white again. So the athlete
was just watching it. He had no idea.
Like he was like, "What am I doing
here?" He just like wouldn't tell him
anything.
>> Yeah.
>> And all a sudden he's like, "Oh, the
screen color." Then he lost focus
>> and then went right back to it and then
started to realize and I don't think he
even had any idea what he was doing
internally.
>> Yeah. Yeah. He was just watching the
screen and eventually was like, I get
it. I get it. I get it. And I was like,
ah.
Because that to me felt like a
transferable skill.
>> Mhm.
>> Because he wasn't going like three in
whole, which I'm like, you can't do this
>> in the middle of a meeting and things
are you're freaking out on traffic.
>> Yep.
>> You have to have that indogous
regulation,
>> which I thought was brilliant. So, first
of all, did I even get that correct? Is
that how that works?
>> You've got a phenomenal memory. So what
happens is it's a it's
>> only of traumatizing events and whenever
I was in your lab it was traumatic for
me
>> traumatic because of my office but um
>> okay there you go.
>> Yeah. So what was happening is that the
heart rate pro or sorry the bio feedback
was program was measuring the coherence
and the balance between sympathetic
nervous and sympathetic parasympathetic
>> and if it was in a state of high
coherence it would lead to the colors
changing and then if it came out of that
it would stop changing the color. Couple
things with that. Number one, athletes
need to do this because they'll find
that the the harder they try, the harder
it gets. And sometimes Oh, it is the
worst.
>> Yeah. Sometimes athletes just need to be
and they they they can't force it. They
just have to allow it.
>> Yeah. This is why we pull numbers from
people
>> a lot cuz this actually is the worst.
They're holding on to number patterns
>> and you're like your heart rate's at
190. What are we doing here? Like you
got to get off of this. Yeah. So the
hyperco competitive ones we can't do it
with.
>> It's great for them to see it though.
>> Yep. It's great for them to see it.
Secondly, with that is the mantra that I
use a lot is, you know, when you're
feeling it in that moment.
You cannot control your performance
until you can control yourself.
And you can't do anything with yourself
until you could first just change one
thing. The simplest thing, the thing you
were already doing, the thing you were
never taught, it's the first thing you
do when you when you're alive. It's the
last thing you do before you die. Just
do something with that. Let's do
something thoughtful with it. and let's
do something to take all that what's
going on around here and just
internalize a little bit to a sense of
this is what regulation means. So I'm
feeling nervous. I'm feeling goes back
to the I'm going to have a reaction but
what's next? What do I want to do next?
Well, in this case I just want to do
some breathing. That's all I want to do.
And that can have a a major impact
especially when it's coupled with them
seeing it and then hopefully seeing it
again. I always send them the the graph.
They love the graph and the picture of
it and everything. Yeah. Are there any
tools people can use at home that are
similar to that is that commercially
available software are there other ones
that if they don't have a sports
psychologist office to go to uh whether
this is technology they can buy or
software programs books any if someone
wanted to work on bio feedback directly
what do you like to tell people
>> so I'm going to hesitate with that
number one I haven't looked into it for
the lay person in a long time and I have
a feeling if I attempt to do that I'm
going to either be wrong or lead
something Okay, just tell us what you
use or what your colleagues use maybe.
>> So this company is HeartMath and
>> Oh yeah, HeartMath is the the most
popular one, right?
>> It is. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Heart math.
>> Exactly like it sounds. Yeah.
>> They have the more expensive sort of
full desktop products. They've got some
in the field stuff you can use. There's
a program that you can get called inner
balance and that's where it's very much
activated with the phone and a lot less
expensive than some of the more lab type
equipment that you might get. Inner
balance is something I would look into.
They have the in the field stuff. You
can pair with your phone or your iPad or
whatever and you can do stuff. Those are
probably the two that I know best right
now. I I I would have needed to take a
little bit of time before I made any
sort of public recommendations about
what other options there are. I just
don't look for those things.
>> Fair. Uh Neurotracker.
>> So Neurotracker
I I'll get sometimes it feels weekly.
I'll get these cold calls, emails,
LinkedIn messages. say, "We have this
brain training thing. Can we test it to
you? Can we send you this product?" And
I turned almost all of them down. And
for years and years and years, I haven't
>> knowing you for how long I've known you.
That that that's very funny to me
because I'm like, "Oh, I'm sure you're
turning it." I know you are like I and I
know how that turnown probably looks.
>> Neurotracker is a program and I'm not in
any way paid by them, affiliated with
them at all. Um,
>> you buy it at normal prices.
>> Neurotr maybe you won't have to buy
anymore after this podcast, but go
ahead. that has been a wonderful tool
and it in essence
helps the brain adapt to two things with
respect to our focus and attention. One
is selective attention. So in the
presence of any number of stimuli in our
environment, what do we want to focus on
and what do we want to not focus on and
ignore. So selective attention is
massive in sports in which you've got
officials and stands and rain and all
these things. You got you need to be
able to be really really locked in on
only the stimuli in your environment
that's going to help you perform and
then in the presence of other ones learn
to ignore it. So selective attention and
then sustained attention the ability to
focus up time. Those are two massive
things in a lot of sports. Neurotracker
is a program that an athlete can do to
get better at both focusing on only
those things in their environment they
want to focus on and ignore the others
and do it over time. And what this looks
like then is that you'll sit in front of
a screen and you have 3D goggles on
glasses and there are eight targets on
the screen. They look like tennis balls.
They're circles.
Four of them highlight momentarily and
the highlight disappears. And then all
eight targets move around the screen in
3D space. They go up, down, side to
side, front, back for 8 seconds. And
then all the targets stop. And then each
target has a different number from 1 to
eight and the performer has to call out
the four numbers of the targets that
they think were initially highlighted.
Is this Are you familiar with this at
all? Have you ever seen this before?
>> I've never seen it done. I've seen you
use various light uh tools and tactics
and boards that we had a fuller.
>> Yeah. And goggles where you can see uh
that have cameras shooting back into
people's eyes. You can see where they
were paying attention to. Remember all
these little tools. You used to have a
lot of fun stuff in your lab.
>> And I used to be so mad cuz your lab was
three times the size of mine.
>> You so deserve that lab space.
>> God, it was the worst. Literally the
perfect spot for me.
>> You totally did.
>> And you ruined it all.
>> But we had decades of yoga sweat in the
carpet. So there's a bit of a trade-off.
Okay, let's get refocus again. So, eight
targets on the screen. Four are
highlighted. Highlights disappear for 8
seconds. The targets move around. They
stop. The performers that call out the
four numbers of the targets are
originally targeted. If they get any one
wrong, the next trial goes slower. If
they got all four correct, the next
trial goes faster. There's 20 trials in
a single session. Takes six minutes
start to finish. And it gives you a
very, very specific score. It gives you
a number of data that I really love, but
it gives you a score called the adaptive
speed threshold. And that score
indicates the speed at which the targets
are going that you can correctly get
four targets half the time. That's what
that number is. Most important thing. So
I have athletes who come into my office
and who do this and it's um phenomenal
the improvement they see. number one and
some sports I will never propose use
this because it's not doesn't benefit
them but think about like tennis
think about a goalkeeper in soccer right
like processing all that information and
having to track information and the ball
gets behind three opponents and now they
lose it for a moment and like some of
the transferability is massive
number one number two the regularity
with with which they're in my office
opens up the door for all kinds of other
conversations that with some athletes
would have maybe never happened if we
didn't have that first
>> sort of thing. So
>> the neurot tracker is another really
great tool I think and then neurot
tracker claims that any improvements in
your score are actual changes in the
brain.
I suppose
that we talk a lot about when you get
distracted
when does it occur when you miss a
trial? Oh, I right at the very beginning
that's when I'll lose it. Tell me about
your sleep recently or do you have
finals or do you have like you can you
can get so much into what's happening in
their life when the neurot tracker
scores are lower than what you might
might normally expect and then you can
sort of dive into now okay tell me about
what's going on here and it usually
indicates oh we got to do something
different in our lives to be able to get
better sleep or focus better manage the
situation better or you know midterms
are going to be over next week so you're
going to be in it right now and you can
recover so I've just found is another
really great tool to be able to give
immediate feedback on cognitive
processes that are happening and some of
the tools and techniques that athletes
can use to get better at those things.
We've been tinkering around with this
program we call brain gains for probably
a year and a half now. We were doing it
and I had a bunch of my friends and my
KU pilot were doing like a 10-week pilot
study on it and zero of my friends did
it. Like no, everyone signed up.
Everyone got the stuff. They did the
baseline testing and then no one would
do the training. And I was trying to
figure out why won't these people do and
myself I was just like struggling to get
myself to go through it. And I realized
because when I do that 15 to 20 minute
session and it's not the same setup as
one you mentioned but it's very very
similar where you have to pay tremendous
attention. You get a little bit
physically fatigued.
>> Oh yeah.
>> But you have to pay tremendous attention
and I it snapped in my brain very
recently.
Oh, I'm afraid of being cognitively
tired.
>> Yeah.
>> And I'm like it has nothing to do with
me because I'm like oh I just don't have
time. Blah blah blah. And I'm like, "No,
no, no, no." And my friends, I'm totally
projecting on them. But I I think it was
the same thing cuz I kept I started
asking, "Why are you doing it? Oh my
god, I'm so excited about it. I want to
do it. All these things are coming." I'm
like, "Oh,
>> it's the fact that when you strap into
this thing, it's it's like 15 minutes
long."
>> Yeah.
>> It's you're going to be so tired. You
have to stay so focused. And there's
very few times
in our lives where you have to force
cognitive focus. Right now when I'm
working I will land in that spot but I I
can roll into it if I want. Like I can
break I can there's no breaking that
thing. And I realized after I've done it
a few times I'm like oh I'm avoiding
this fatigue. I'm just avoiding the
mental fatigue that comes with this
thing that I know is it's like it's like
saying I'll do a cross word puzzle
starting a timer and not giving yourself
any chance to do anything until you
finish it.
>> Yeah.
>> Once you start you know you have to
finish and it sucks. And I that is when
this aspect of mental fatigue hit me.
And then it also hit me going, "Oh, I
see the tremendous value here."
Most of my coaching of course is on the
physical side. And so thinking, how much
are we seeing physical fatigue just
being a manifestation of this person is
very tied with paying attention?
>> Yeah.
>> Right now. And you've done some stuff on
things like that.
>> Mhm. What is film session? What are
study sessions look like? How do we make
those things more effective?
Less fatiguing when we know I'm assuming
that the neurot tracker tool itself is a
probably good way to do that. But are
there other maybe quick tips or tools
that the average person can use if
either they're in a sport where they're
doing a lot of film session or like kind
of the me not you know actually tactics
or those in other settings where you're
just like the cognitive fatigue of of
your job your life is how do we make
that training session more effective and
less fatiguing.
>> I'm going to tell you something that I
think is super powerful that is not
related to that
>> great team session.
>> Well, you're in charge. So you Yeah. Ask
a better question and give me a better
answer.
>> No, no, no, no. So art, attention race
res restoration theory. Humans spend
most of their day distracted.
>> I totally their attention being pulled
in a 100 different directions or in a
state of cognitive fatigue because
usually how people take breaks is to
just look at their phone and scroll and
more cognitive fatigues. Humans don't do
a really good job of restoring their
their attention. And there's a theory of
uh attention restoration theory where if
you just take a very short walk in a
natural setting, just that three, five
minutes of that doing not with your
phone on, not with music on, just you
walking and coming back, you will have
had a tremendous restoration of your
ability to cognitive focus and your
cognitive fig fatigue goes down
significantly.
If you are a listener and you're
thinking about how that re um how that
plays out in your day-to-day job, if you
can find instead of just using that time
to go on Instagram, just put your phone
and go walk somewhere outside with trees
or something and come back. It's a
massive way of doing it. So that's a a
relatively new concept, I think, of
using outdoor spaces to walk and clear
our mind from that cognitive fatigue
that most humans have access to. When it
comes to like something like film
sessions, got to break it up. It should
not be too long. I know film sessions go
anywhere from 30 minutes to an hour.
>> I play college football. We were I would
say 60 minutes would have been on a
short side.
>> Yeah. It's just way too
>> 90 minutes.
>> You got to do this post practice, post
shower, post dinner.
>> You're all over it.
>> It's over. Do it before.
>> Do it before you're physically tired.
Do it in small segments.
Ask a lot of questions versus just like
throwing it all at them. Like engage
with them. Enga do it approach it like
you would as a professor or a teacher.
>> Teacher,
>> have someone come up and explain like
engage them as much as possible. You
don't see that a lot. You see a lot of
the coaches just over and over again.
And you just sit there and
>> number one, you're going to be a little
bit more focused because you're going to
be on your toes knowing the coach is
about to ask me a question. That's a
brilliant strategy. But number two, it
keeps them engaged. you just don't see
that. You got to build that engagement
in somehow and the athletes are capable
of doing it, right? You I believe you
need to also have footage that's
positive and that builds the athletes
confidence. I think most film sessions
they walk out of there and it's all the
stuff they did bad or all the other team
what they're doing good and almost none
>> of the positive stuff. So, you've got to
build a motivational tool into it and
somehow embed in kind of like the 321
approach. Like, I would I would consider
that a very similar approach to it. Um,
the film session stuff is is big. My
office at Cal is right across from the
film room where a lot of our teams do it
and I just I hear it. I'm right across
the office from them. And there's some
great sessions. There are some coaches
that do it really well and there's also
some coaches that just go, "Wow, that's
twice as long as they're probably
capable of really."
>> What's the time here? Is this 20
minutes? Is this an hour? Like what's
the number?
>> I would do more frequent shorter ones if
I could do
>> pre and postpractice for 20 minutes each
or something like that.
>> Yeah.
>> If you can.
>> Yeah. That makes
>> some teams do two days a week.
>> If someone has listened to all this and
thought, "Wow, this is a really
interesting field." Whether I am a sport
coach and it doesn't matter, right?
Because if you are going over game film
or if you're teaching someone at your
company a workshop, the exact same
principles apply here, right?
>> Yeah.
>> What kind of person, what kind of
qualifications, what are the right
terms, where can they learn more, help
people that are want to tinker in this
field,
what to avoid, what's what's the not
real stuff. You get what I'm trying to
say here. What organizations where
>> Sure.
>> And without being elitist, of course,
but get it. If you're looking for mental
health provision and you need to work
with a clinical psychologist then you
need to work with somebody who has the
lenture in clinical psychology whether
they have sport related training or not
and that's a really important thing.
>> Yeah. Because some clinical
psychologists will also work with sport.
>> That's correct.
>> Yeah.
>> Yep. But those people also need to have
the training and certifications in sport
settings. So the mental performance
piece is the the gold standard
certification is the CMPC. It's a
certified mental performance consultant
certification.
>> So that is a legitimate certification
that that is very rigorous. That's not a
weekend.
>> No, no, no, no, no. You need a master's
degree from McCrenity University. You
need to be able to get supervised with a
certain number of hours. You need to be
able to pass the testing to do so.
>> This is very akin to being a a physical
therapist.
>> Yeah. You need to attend professional
conferences to maintain your
certification.
>> Say that one more time to us. What that
one is?
>> It's the certified mental performance
consultant certification. It's the
association for applied sports
psychology. They offer that. I'll say a
couple things just in the 30 years I've
been in the field. I've seen a lot of
trends. I think one of the trends I've
seen is that in the past people who
wanted to get work in this field needed
to get clinical lensure and mental
health provision because the NC2A that's
all they were really hiring for example
and professional sport teams were hiring
licensed psychologists and
um we still need that and if somebody
has an interest in working in mental
health and we need good people to do
those things and we need that support
but we also have a lot of people who
want to do performance based performance
psych mental performance and those
people should be able to do that without
having to go and get lenture and mental
health training and and so I'm seeing
the pendulum shift towards that for
people who want to go into that who want
to get a master's degree or a PhD in
that field who want to get certification
who want to do the work to get it we
need more positions
um I wasn't going to promote the cal but
I think what we're doing at Cal is a
phenomenal model for what this could
look like. If a student athlete I'm
working with needs mental health
support, we've got a team of people we
can refer him to. We're there for the
performance and the sport well-being of
our student athletes. And if more
universities could hire that model,
people who want to work the coaches,
people who want to be at practice,
people who want to be in the rain with
our our men's rowing team, then they
should be there should be more
opportunities for those things to
happen. And I'm hoping people hear that.
I know that people are going to walk
away from this with a ton of of
practical tactical tools as well as I
hope a just a broader understanding of
what this field really actually is and
the opportunities in front of us. If we
look across the landscape of high
performance
sports or not, there's a couple of areas
that to me are really underserved.
Sleep is a big one of them and this is
part and parcel to that. You just do not
see enough high performance groups.
Yeah,
>> adopting real truth specialists in these
areas in my opinion. So, I I thank you
for all that information. I know that
people are going to get a lot from that.
Uh it was great to see you again. It's
been a long time.
>> Yeah.
>> And uh yeah, it's been a true pleasure,
man. So, thank you so much for
everything you've done and for the great
information and for all the years of
friendship.
>> I miss you and I'll see you in 10 years.
>> Ah, my friend.
>> Cheers.
Thank you for joining for today's
episode. My goal, as always, is to share
exciting scientific insights that help
you perform at your best. If the show
resonates with you and you want to help
ensure this information remains free and
accessible to anyone in the world, there
are a few ways that you can support.
First, you can subscribe to the show on
YouTube, Spotify, and Apple. And on
Apple and Spotify, you can leave us up
to a five-star review. Subscribing and
leaving a review really does help us a
lot. Also, please check out our
sponsors. The show would not exist
without them and their exceptional
products and services. Finally, you can
share today's episode with a friend who
you think would enjoy it. If you have
any content questions or suggestions,
please put those in the comments section
on YouTube. I really do try my best to
read them all and to see what you have
to say. I use my Instagram and
ex-profiles also exclusively for
scientific communication. So, those are
great places to follow along for more
learning. My handle is Dr. Andy Galpin
on both platforms. We also have an email
newsletter that distills all of our
episodes in the most actionable
takeaways. We have newsletters on how to
improve fitness in V2 max, how to build
muscle and strength, and much more. To
subscribe to the newsletter, just go to
performpodcast.com
and click newsletter. It's completely
free and we do not share your email with
anybody. Thank you for listening. And
never forget, in the famous words of
Bill Bowererman, if you have a body, you
are an athlete.